<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two godly and fruitfull treatises the one, vpon the Lords prayer. The other, vpon the sixe principles. Both penned by that learned man, Paul Baine, sometimes preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850722</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 950:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two godly and fruitfull treatises the one, vpon the Lords prayer. The other, vpon the sixe principles. Both penned by that learned man, Paul Baine, sometimes preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 276 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the great South-doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A treatise vpon the sixe principles" has separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>Register and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO GODLY AND FRVITFVLL TREATISES: The one, <hi>Vpon the Lords Prayer:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other, <hi>Vpon the ſixe Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both penned by that learned man, <hi>Paul Baine,</hi> ſometimes Preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Field</hi> for <hi>Robert Mylbourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the great South-doore of Paules. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15947:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15947:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the honorable</hi> SIR THOMAS SMITH Knight, late Embaſſadour from his Maieſty to the Emperour of Ruſſia, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the famous So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties trading to the Eaſt Indies, Muſcouia, &amp;c. all bleſſings of this life and the next.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable Sir, that Axiome in morall Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie ſo often vſed, that <hi>Bonum eſt ſui diffuſiuum,</hi> Good is of a ſpreading nature,
<pb facs="tcp:15947:3"/> hath preuailed with me to go on in further pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing a parcell of the writings of that worthie Diuine and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, Maiſter <hi>PAVL BAINE.</hi> The former tractates that are abroad, I heare to be thankfully entertained in the Church of God. And therefore the Printers ſtill importune me to ſet forth that which remaineth vnpubliſhed; almoſt chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging me as one that inuert to my priuate good, ſuch things as ſhould be communicated for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefit. Which aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:15947:3"/> that I may wipe off from my ſelfe, I haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen way to the printing of the two enſuing vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Treatiſes. To the which that I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed your honourable name, let it not (I beſeech you) ſeeme any preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For there being many ends of dedicating bookes, yet the two moſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed, are to procure countenance to the bookes ſo dedicated, and to teſtifie the thankfulneſſe of the Dedicators. Both which ends I confeſſe my ſelfe to haue aimed at in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication: howbeit the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:15947:4"/> beareth with me the greater ſway. For hauing my ſelfe, honoured Sir, taſted the fruites of your loue, yet my deſire is, not onely to be thankfull to you for my ſelfe, but much more for the many, and great kindneſſes, a long time continued to my deare Parents. To whom what is it you could well do, and haue not largely performed? The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars I need not proclaime, what perſonall loue you haue vouchſafed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; what bountie (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times) by my louing mothers hand, you haue
<pb facs="tcp:15947:4"/> ſent to releeue the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of diuerſe poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who haue bleſſed God for you in that behalfe. Go on thus ſtill, worthie Knight, to do well; and as you haue had the honour of religious profeſſion heretofore, ſo prouide that your laſt dayes may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with ſuch fruites, as are found with them that flouriſh in the Courts of our God, (as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith) who ſtill bring forth fruite in old age,<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.13.14.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fat, and flouriſhing. To the helping forward of which things, if this good &amp; godly Manuel may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,
<pb facs="tcp:15947:5"/> (as vpon diligent reading I truſt it will) I ſhall praiſe the Lord, whom I beſeech heartily to bleſſe your ſelfe, and your vertuous Ladie, with the young Knight your onely iſſue liuing.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Lime-ſtreete <date>the <hi>11.</hi> of December. <hi>1618.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Readie at your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his power, <hi>E. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15947:5"/>
                  <head>A Treatiſe vpon the <hi>LORDS</hi> Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His prayer hath three parts, the firſt is the Preface; in which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared whom we muſt pray vnto, in theſe words: <hi>O our Father which art in heauen.</hi> The ſecond part is the prayer it ſelfe, ſtanding on ſixe petitions. The laſt is the Concluſion, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth a reaſon why we pray to God alone; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15947:6"/> the kingdome, which is all authority to grant our requeſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him: the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that is, all abilitie to execute our deſires, is with him: the glory, that is, all this honour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acknowledged a fountain of good things, belongeth to him a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery good gift deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; who in this regard is onely to be inuocated and praiſed. From the Preface in generall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue; <hi>No Angels or Saints departed, but God our Father onely muſt be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15947:6"/> inuocated of vs.</hi> In no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be carefull,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> but let your requeſts be known to God with thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: Whatſoeuer you aske my Father in my name, you ſhall receiue it. What an vnſeemely thing were it, that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould ſeeke to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in the houſe for ſupplie of what they want, not to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parents? ſo here. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, we cannot call vpon any religiouſly, on whom we may not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. Rom. 10. Now to deriue faith from any creature is a thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15947:7"/> Ier. 17. Curſed is he that maketh fleſh his arme, and is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from the Lord. Thirdly, to pray faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (that is, ſo as we are perſwadéd that we ſhall receiue that we aske) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth knowledge of three things: Firſt, that the partie we pray to or call on, doth heare vs to know our deſires: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that he is willing to helpe vs: Thirdly, that he hath ability to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what he willeth. Now for mentall praiers the Angels often can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know them; God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15947:7"/> who only ſearcheth the hearts and reines, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth ſuch prayers as are mentall and vocall: the Saints in heauen haue no meanes how to vnderſtand them, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing the Scripture teacheth. I know mans preſumption voucheth many reaſons why An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhould heare vocall prayers; which are as eaſily reiected as reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Had they know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet the other things are doubtfull; for they can do nothing which they will not, and they will not do any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15947:8"/> thing to which God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them not; they are ſo perfectly conformed to his pleaſure, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his beckoning in all things. Fourthly, it is his will to be called on, and ſo to performe that he knoweth we want; and he is both willing and able to ſupply it vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>We may argue from this prayer thus: That which is a perfect plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme of prayer, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as perfectly who muſt be called on, as it teacheth what is to be asked: But this is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15947:8"/> forme of praier, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching fully what things ſoeuer may be asked; Therefore it teacheth vs fully what kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be called on. <hi>Ob.</hi> The Sonne and the Spirit are not here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed? <hi>An.</hi> The Father excludeth all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are pure crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, not perſons which haue the ſame ſingular eſſence with him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, theſe are not named, becauſe ſuch is the diuine diſpenſation, that though whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one is inuocated all are inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; yet the Father is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15947:9"/> fitly alone named, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sonne hath the part of a Mediator, through whom we go to the Father; and the Spirit the office of a ſchoolemaſter, teaching what to pray, and as we ought. Whence the Councell decreed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not Chriſt, nor the Spirit ſhould be named in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting publike prayers to God; a plaine argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the naming of Saints was not dreamed of by thoſe times. Let vs then make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Lord our ſtrong Tower, to which we flie ſeeking
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15947:9"/> ſaluation. Parents loue not when their children are ſtrange towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſtand aloofe, being in the meane while affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough to others. No, let vs not with God ioyne others. Men loue not to be ſorted in any buſineſſe but with their peeres and equals; ſo neither ſhall the liuing God like to be matched with his creatures.</p>
                  <p>Now in particular. Firſt, that he ſetteth downe not a ſingle forme, but a forme of ſpeech of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conioyned, it doth teach, that <hi>We muſt not,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15947:10"/> becauſe we pray alone, be careleſſe of ioyning with others in prayer.</hi> He tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his diſciples ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pray, Our Father, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> and, Where two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I am in the midſt of them. Looke as if a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle priſoner ſhould aske vs ought, it hath his force; but when all in the houſe lift vp their voices at once, it is much more piercing; ſo in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which letteth vs ſee how wide ſuch are, who will make light of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with other, they hope they may pray for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15947:10"/> themſelues, and like the old ſaying, Euery man for himſelfe &amp; God for vs all.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, hence we note that <hi>in our prayers we muſt be mindfull of others as wel as our ſelues.</hi> For as he teacheth them to pray, and to ſay, Our Father, becauſe they were more then one ioyntly before him; ſo in this regard that he might make them mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of all their brethren, called, or vncalled, that belong to the election of God:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.18.</note> Watch vnto prayer for all Saints; not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15947:11"/> that we may not make a prayer wherein we muſt not mention others, but becauſe wee muſt not faile at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient times in the exerciſe of praier, to mention others as wel as our ſelues, ſeeking their peace with God. We are members of one body: and therfore muſt helpe one another; and ſuch as haue learned loue and mercy, cannot but ſeeke at God the proſperity of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whoſe conflicting ſtate they know by good experience in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues; wherfore we muſt ſtirre
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15947:11"/> our ſelues vp to the faithfull performance of this dutie. He were a graceleſſe childe that would neuer pray for his mother; &amp; we would thinke he would do lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for vs, that would not lend vs a good word here or there: ſo when we remember not the Church, and will not open our mouthes one for another to God, what loue is there? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, let vs therefore frequent this dutie, not in word or ſhew, but in deed and truth. From the practiſe of this dutie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15947:12"/> it cometh to paſſe that a Chriſtian man is like a rich merchant, who hath his factors in diuers countries: ſo a Chriſtian man hath in all places of the world ſome that deale for him with God (that neuer ſaw his face) who are petitioners for him vnto God. Thirdly, hence that he teacheth vs to pray, Our Father, we learne, that <hi>We muſt in prayer to God come with loue to the brethren.</hi> If thou art about to offer thy ſacrifice at the altar,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.23.24.</note> and remembreſt thou haſt any thing againſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15947:12"/> thy brethren, go, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile thy ſelfe firſt, then do thy duty after; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Lord will turne away from our prayer. If one ſhould giue the King a petition, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in his hand, or about him, ſome ſtinking ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour which the ſence of any abhorred, could he thinke but the King would turne from him? So he that cometh peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning to God with wrath and malice, which ſtinketh odiouſly in Gods noſtrils, muſt look that God will turne his countenance from him.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15947:13"/> Hence Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.7.</note> that by wrath prayers are troubled; wherefore let vs labor to be of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. Should our parents know that we are fallen forth with our brethren, durſt we come in their ſight? would we looke for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to be checked from them? euen ſo the Lord will turne his back to our prayers, while our affections are turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our brethren. Further, obſerue hence both a ground of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and hope, when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15947:13"/> we come to deale with God: If I be a Father,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> where is my reuerence? We come with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence before our earthly Princes, and in all our geſtures expreſſe it: how much more muſt this be in vs, when we haue to deale with the liuing God? for this Father is impartiall in iuſtice, that we haue need to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe before him in feare. Againe, it is a ground of hope; earthly parents will not deny their children good things: much leſſe ſhall God deny vs his Spirit,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15947:14"/> and what euer thing is good for vs. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth rebuke the rudeneſſe of ſome that care not how vnprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red they fall vpon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, how rude geſture they vſe in it, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly they breake away after it, vſing their Father as if he were a cypher, or a father of clouts, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a God that will without reſpect of perſons iudge euery one. Our doubting minds muſt hence be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. How confidently do children come to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15947:14"/> their parents? If we haue a ſuite to a friend which is reaſonable, we will preſume it; how much more may wee be of good hope in all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts which we make to God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> By manifeſting the effect of glory; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he filleth heauen &amp; earth, yea all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is with him as a moate within the light of the Sunne; but looke as a King who by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; power ruleth ouer all his kingdome, is at the Court more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15947:15"/> diſplaying there the glory of his maieſty: ſo God whoſe eſſence and preſence of powers is euery where, in the heauens as in the Court of his Maieſty, doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his glory more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently.</p>
                  <p>Obſerue then; that <hi>In coming to God we muſt ſet before vs his heauenly Maieſty.</hi> For this ſtirreth vp reuerence, moueth deuotion, making vs to be heauenly minded, ſtrengthening our faith. The gliſter of the pomp of earthly Princes doth moue the ſubiect to all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15947:15"/> humble regard of them, to al ſeemly ſubmiſneſſe in their behauiours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the not being ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this way, doth make vs ſo looſe and heedleſſe when we approach to God. Againe, this doth admoniſh vs to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly minded, if we will haue any coniunction with God: for as he that would ſpeak to the King at Court, muſt bodily moue himſelfe thither where the King bideth; ſo we that would ſpeake with God, who dwelleth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15947:16"/> in heauenly glory (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all this viſible frame of the creature) we muſt in ſpirit by faith moue our hearts thither, where he is. Beſides, where our Father is, there our country is: <hi>Vbi pater ibi patria:</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as pilgrimes and ſtrangers do long after their natiue ſoiles, ſo muſt we after that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inheritance, which our father in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reſerueth for vs. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it confirmeth vs in our faith: being in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he both ſeeth our wants, and is of all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15947:16"/> ſtrength and power to effect our deſires. Our God is in heauen, and doth whatſoeuer he will. Parents earthly who haue large hearts, haue ſhort hands, though they wiſh vs well, yet they haue no power to effect what they would; Were it thus with our Father, faith were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wanteth not will as a father, nor power as a heauenly gouernour, our faith is firmly vnderpropped. How then are we to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſelues, who know not how ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15947:17"/> to admire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore an earthly maieſty, a mortall man, and yet are ſo reſpectleſſe of the high excellency of God? How ſlow of heart are we, that we are not rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp higher then theſe earthly things, when we are to deale with our God glorious in the heauens? Why do wee dread and truſt in the power of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not awing nor hauing confidence in this power, when the power of euery creature higher then the earth is vnreſiſtable by it? as what power of fleſh can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15947:17"/> reſiſt the leaſt cloud fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dropping his raine, the leaſt ſtarre from ſending forth his light and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? What a power is this of the Creator of al theſe things, who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in glorie aboue them? Let vs therefore conſidering this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, glory our Father hath, grow vp to more reuerence, deuotion, and affiance towards him. Now follow the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in which I will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this order: Firſt, to open the phraſe of them where it is needfull. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15947:18"/> of euery petition. Thirdly, conſiderations how we may feelingly come to make our ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall requeſts to God. Fourthly, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions which may be drawne from them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hallowed be thy Name.</hi> Name is put here for God, by name, or any other wayes notified, that is, made knowne to vs: Name put for the perſon named, as Acts 1.15, by a Metonymie of the adiunct, and ſo named, one kind of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting a perſon, for all other, by a Synecdoche.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15947:18"/> 
                     <hi>Hallowed</hi> here ſignifieth to be manifeſted, and acknowledged holy; as wiſdome is iuſtified of her children: ſo declared to be, and approoued of thoſe that embrace her. The ſumme is, that God wold ſo worke, that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe howſoeuer made knowne by titles, word or works, may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of vs as holy, and ſo confeſſed, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly reſpected of vs; that God would effect this that himſelfe may be more and more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored of vs, who are his choſen, and in all others
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15947:19"/> that are the children of deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt then, here we aske that God would worke all ſuch things as may be matter of his praiſe, whether they be good things towards his children, or iudgements vpon the wicked. For thus God doth honour himſelfe, when he doth ſuch things before vs, vpon which we take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to honour him. Hence it is that he will win honor to his Name in deliuering his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted that iudgement
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15947:19"/> on <hi>Aarons</hi> ſonnes, he ſaid, he would be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in ſuch as come neare him: if he might not haue it from them, he wold haue it in them, by ſending ſuch iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on them, as might be matter of his glorie.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we aske of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> God to refraine the bringing of ſuch things vpon vs, which might make wicked ones take occaſion to prophane his Name. For when God ſaith, he will not pollute his Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen, by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15947:20"/> the vtter extinguiſhing of his people, he doth teach vs that the giuing occaſion to wicked ones to crow againſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and himſelfe their God, is a diſhonor of his Maieſtie; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here we pray it may be preuented. Yet if it ſo fall out that the ſtate of Gods people is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible, and they will not be reclaimed from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning Gods Name, it is better that the open enemy ſhould blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme them, then that he ſhould receiue ſuch intollerable indignity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15947:20"/> from his owne people.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we aske y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God would make vs grow vp to acknowledge him, in all meanes, and wayes of his, wherein he manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth his glory. For as the Sun ſhining bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhould be glorious in it ſelfe, but if eyes were not opened to behold it, it ſhould not be had in accompt as glorious with man; ſo the Lord, glorious in all his wayes, hath not that glorie in his creature, till, the eye of the mind opened, this be diſcerned of them.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15947:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, we aske that he would enable vs in ſpirit, word, and worke, to giue him glory from our ſelues, and ſeeke that others may do the ſame, moued by our words &amp; works; that as we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne him to be holy &amp; glorious euery way, ſo we may accordingly glorifie him. For theſe may be diſtinguiſhed; yea ſeuered, Rom. 1.21. that we might be zealous of his glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, for others as yet vncalled, they are two-fold, belonging to the election of grace, or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15947:21"/> otherwiſe. Now for the former we intreate that God would daily bring them home to glorifie him with vs, yea that he would giue them godly ſorrow for ſuch things as before their viſitation they heedleſly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, Pſal. 67. For other we pray, that God wold reſtraine them from their high prophanation of his Name, and that he would turne their rage (and ſo by proportion all their other ſinnes) to the praiſe of his Name, Pſal. 18. Now to ſay this petition feelingly, wee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15947:22"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider. Firſt, how neceſſary a thing it is that God ſhould haue his glory: for to this end all things were made, we liue, moue, and haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> purpoſe. Secondly, though this is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, yet how little God is honoured by vs who are his, he paſſing by vs in many parts of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence we not ſeeing him, nor taking any heed to him in the things we do ſee; not affected with feare, ioy, thankfulneſſe as they require, little thinking on him, not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15947:22"/> ſpeaking of him to his praiſe, not ordering all our works in ſuch ſort as they might be to the glorie of him our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes do we take his Name in vaine? Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we muſt conſider how our hearts are ſo poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with loue of our owne names, eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; that glory which is from man, that we are altogether careleſſe of Gods glory. Hence it is that if we circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo faile, that it cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our reputation in any kind with men, it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15947:23"/> doth ſting vs; but when we fault towards God, we paſſe it ouer well enough. Hence it is that if one put the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous behauiour vpon vs, vſing a terme of any diſgrace, it doth kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle cooles preſently; but we can heare Gods Name diſhonored, and not be affected, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with it. We had need therefore to pray vnto God, that he would heale this matter. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to marke how fearefully with wicked ones not yet called, Gods Name is propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15947:23"/> Doth it not pittie vs when we heare that our friends haue ſuch ſeruants as do twentie diſhoneſt parts, which will redound to their diſcredit? Did we ſee their giuing no regard to their maiſter, rioting his goods otherwiſe then he commandeth, drinking themſelues drunke in his cellers, would it not grieue vs? Thus that Lord of vs all, that Maiſter in heauen is vſed by thoſe that ſhould be ſeruants vnto him; which if we will weigh, we cannot
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15947:24"/> but crie to him for helpe that thoſe deluges of his diſhonour might be ſtopped and diminiſhed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, Gods promiſes to ſuch as ſeeke his glory, and threatning to ſuch as do otherwiſe; he will honour ſuch as honour him, and ſuch as deſpiſe him ſhall be deſpiſed. Theſe things pondered, wil ingender ſome more feeling when we preferre this petition. The things to be collected are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that the chiefe thing that we are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, is that God may more &amp; more be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15947:24"/> this is to be dearer to vs then our owne ſoules, which made <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo affected, that they could with the hazard of their ſoules haue promoted it. Rom. 10. We ſee it hath the firſt place; this is more worthy then all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beſides. The end is more worthie, then that which ſerueth to the end; as meate and drink which ſerue to maintain the bodily life, are not ſo good as the body. So when all the creature &amp; all the actions of vs, are to tend hither, that God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15947:25"/> may be glorified, it is ſure that Gods glorie is farre more excellent; which muſt make vs ſeeke that he be more &amp; more ſanctified of vs. We ſee that ſeruants of honourable perſonages they are all for their Lords honour; they will runne into bookes, and out of good inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſometimes, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a kind of gallancy, which graceth, as they thinke, the perſonage they ſerue; ſhall not we to our great good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our God? O let vs ſeeke it. Who will keepe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15947:25"/> a ſeruant no way to his credit? no more wil God let vs retaine vnto him alwayes, if we be ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to him this way.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, when we ſeeke this at God, we confeſſe it is God that teacheth and enableth vs to honour him. Our children haue no beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours more ciuill, to our credit, which we do not traine them vnto. None by nature vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, none enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth after God; nor yet care to glorifie him as God; as he is the God that teacheth vs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15947:26"/> in all points ſo in this. The vſe of it is to teach vs to referre all vnto God, that we do proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly this way, who worketh it in vs, not our ſelues; as alſo to teach vs on whom we muſt hang with conſcience of our own wants, that we may more and more be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled this way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, hence we ſee what care we muſt haue neither to diſhonour God our ſelues, nor to partake with it in others: for ſo doing we ſeeme to mocke God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in deed, that which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15947:26"/> we beg in words: he that asketh his daily bread, and is careleſſe to get, or ſaue any thing by ſome lawfull calling, ſhould deride and tempt the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</p>
                  <p>Finally, from hence we perceiue, that ſpying Gods diſhonour, wee muſt be grieued: For who can deſire that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but it will grieue him to ſee the contrary? Yea we muſt by eiaculation of our mind renew our requeſts, (when we ſee ſuch ſpectacles) that God himſelf would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for the maintaining
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15947:27"/> the honour of his owne Name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy kingdome come.</hi> A kingdome is ſuch an order or ſtate of men, in which one gouerneth, the reſt are ſubiect, vnto their good. So Gods kingdome is ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or eſtate, wherein God hath all ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and men acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelues liege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to his Maieſty, to their great benefit tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and eternall. For the kingdome of power is not here meant vnder which the diuels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues liue: but that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15947:27"/> of heauen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied by <hi>Daniel:</hi> which is ſuch a gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in which God moſt graciouſly ruleth, &amp; we willingly obey, to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happineſſe. This kingdome God ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth partly mediatly by his Vice Roy Ieſus Chriſt; partly immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when Chriſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne vp that Mediator-like kingdome, as hauing now brought all to God his Father. Who then ſhall alone with his Son (as the ſecond perſon, not as Mediator) and Spirit, be all in all. So we
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15947:28"/> pray that God would that the honour of his Name may be ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, make his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpread in the hearts of men, that the number of his ſubiects may be increaſed, and ſubiection augmented, who are all brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, till all be perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the kingdome of glorie.</p>
                  <p>The things that we aske are:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that God would caſt downe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan, and all the props and pillars of it, where yet it is vnſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15947:28"/> in this God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, as a lawfull King in ſubiugating vſurping tyrants.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> would plant both out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and inwardly the externall face, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubſtance of his kingdome where yet it is not.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for our ſelues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> conuerted, that God would roote out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes of darkneſſe in vs; which are as yet not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to his grace.</p>
                  <p>That he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> increaſe in vs all thoſe heauenly vertues
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15947:29"/> that he hath begun of his mercie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That he would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all the enmities and impediments which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than raiſeth to let vs this way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That he would giue vs all meanes ſeruing to this end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, that he would bring vs to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glorie.</p>
                  <p>For ſuch as are vncal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, not belonging to Gods mercy we pray:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That Gods power may bring them on their knees, and that they may be cruſhed with a rod
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15947:29"/> of iron.</p>
                  <p>Motiues to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure asking of thoſe things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to conſider the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> breadth of the diuels poſſeſſion, how potent and numberſome his ſubiects are. Who could ſee the King holding ſome Shire within his kingdome, and enemies ſpread like Graſhoppers ouer the face of all his countrie? Beſides, what good ſubiect that loued the honor of the King, could thinke on this, or the wilt with drie eyes?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15947:30"/> weigh what a glory it is to God, and ſecurity to vs, when true hearted Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites are increaſed, as a Princelike Diademe; ſuch is the multitude of well ordered ſubiects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſtrong battell which this ſtrong man the diuell &amp; his Angels make (hindring the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome nationally or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally) to all ſincere or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, to all the more full conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſubiection of thoſe who are already conuerted from Sathan
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15947:30"/> to God.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to obſerue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> what a deale of darknes and luſts of darkneſſe remaine, like Cananites, as prickes and thornes in vs.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, how prone we <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> are to fall away and be brought backe againe, and how farre we are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being fully ſubdued to God.</p>
                  <p>Finally, what miſeries <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> we are here ſubiect to, what bleſſedneſſe wee want, becauſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is not yet fully come.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things well
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15947:31"/> pondered will make vs feelingly crie to God that his kingdome may come. Doth not euery good ſubiect wiſh the enlargement of the Kings territories, the rooting out of all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, that ſet themſelues againſt the proſperity of his kingdome? So muſt we if we be true ſubiects to the kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Did we border vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Turkiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ſo that we were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten forraged, would it not make vs crie to God for helpe? and ſhall the diuell ſtill ſinke vs in our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15947:31"/> perſons, euery where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uading, and ſhall we be ſilent? What tyrannie to Sathans and ſinnes ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie? What wants to the wants of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace, ioy? &amp;c. in which things Gods kingdome cometh. We ſhould ſeeke it ſo farre as we want it, and ioy in it ſo farre as we partake in it: to be naturaliſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our kingdome is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit great ones eſteeme; but to be within Gods kingdome, ô how bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</p>
                  <p>Doctrines to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:15947:32"/>
                  <p>Firſt, who it is that can trample Sathan vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feet, &amp; diſſolue the workes of the diuell: it is God alone: it is he that muſt turne vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be turned out of the kingdome of darkneſſe. Praier preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth both want of that we aske, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency in our ſelues to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, or that it is out of our power. Againe, the ſtrong man holds poſſeſſion till a ſtronger cometh. Now who is, of any other creature, ſtronger then Sathan, in ſuch degree that to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15947:32"/> caſt him out the Papiſts giue ſome place in this worke to the libertie of our will? But though it be true, we turne becauſe we will turne to God, yet (we will turne) doth note, not the principall cauſe, but a cauſe ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, working by way of free diſpoſition, which diſpoſition it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth from God, not from naturall ſtrength, ſo that ſtill all is by him. Men turne not, becauſe they will not conuert; [becauſe] here noteth the fundamentall, radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, prime cauſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15947:33"/> not conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which the wil doth by way of diſpoſition, which it hath by nature of it ſelfe vnto ſinne. But it is otherwiſe when we ſay, This man conuerts to God becauſe he will conuert; for here God is preſuppoſed the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Agent; man a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary and inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; the habite diſpoſing him to do this, being grace receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, not deriued to him with his nature. Away there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with Papiſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which make the will of man in a manner
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15947:33"/> almightie. God offers grace like as a Merchant ſetteth his wares to ſell, leauing it to our will whether we will buy or no. Were this true, if you aske what diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth me from another vnconuerted? I anſwer, My will; I by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome I had of will, took that proffered, which another by the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie refuſed.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, marke who muſt ſtrengthen, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and perfect all things begun in vs; he ſanctifieth vs through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. Euen as the Sunne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15947:34"/> firſt bringing light, doth more and more ſubdue all the darkneſſe of the aire, till it come to full ſtrength; ſo the ſame God that firſt diſpelleth the darkneſſe of ſinne and ignorance, doth more and more perfect the light begun, till it come to glorie: and as the ſame Phyſition which firſt recouereth vs from ſome deadly lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering euill, muſt after reſtore decayed ſtrength and cleanſe all relickes of ſicke matter, by ſuch diets as Art aduiſeth, ſo God, &amp;c. What then if
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15947:34"/> we ſee all weake, ready to ouerturne; many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in a manner vtterly wanting, ſo weake they are in vs? God that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the things that are not, as if they were, is the beginner and perfecter of his kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that Gods kingdome is but in part come vnto vs; we ſee not all things as yet put vnder him; many not called, many enemies &amp; euils vnſubdued, many works of darkneſſe han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging about vs: which muſt comfort vs, though we find theſe things; we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15947:35"/> could not ſay this praier, were there not matter of this nature ſtill dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with vs, in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting courſe. We are ſaid to be tranſlated out of the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, in regard y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do not volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily ſuffer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him as a lawful King, but vnwillingly as vnder an vſurper too ſtrong for vs. Againe, he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to be, and certainly ſhall be caſt out. Now that is ſaid to be done, which a while is ſo in doing that it certainly ſhall be finiſhed.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, note what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15947:35"/> true Chriſtian muſt ſeeke with his vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeuour, that both himſelf and others be in ſubiection to God. We ſhould with <hi>Ieremie</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> bewaile the auerſeneſſe of others, &amp; rebellions they liue in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: and like <hi>Paul,</hi> bemone the lawes of euill which dwell in vs, &amp;c. Euery one would haue God to ſaue him, but few heartily deſire that God would rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him. How do Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſeeke to propagate the Popes kingdome? They find out new
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15947:36"/> worlds, rather then his ſubiects ſhould not be made vp: &amp; how would a naturall ſubiect grieue to ſpie in himſelfe much falſhood, much rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne? So muſt wee grieue that wee haue hearts ſo falſe and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious againſt God. How do men profeſſe perfect conformitie and totall ſubiection to men?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which words two things are to be noted; firſt, the doing of Gods will: ſecondly the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15947:36"/> manner. The wil of God ſignifieth not his ſecret vnreſiſtable will, but his will as it is reuealed to vs, that we ſhould walke after it. [In earth] Earth, in this place, is put by a Metonymie of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, for men dwelling on the earth. [As it is in heauen] that is, readily in all parts, conſtantly, with ſome reſemblance to the heauenly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, though not with like perfection. The ſumme is, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God reuealeth as his will vnto vs, which he would haue vs do, or
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15947:37"/> by euent maketh known as his will, which wee muſt ſuffer, that we may obey him both in the one and the other; like as the heauenly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures obey him, though not with like perfection. The things we aske are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> theſe: That God would bring ſuch as belong to his mercie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſnare in which they are taken to do the diuels &amp; their owe will, to do his owne pleaſure and worke in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> his vineyard. Secondly, for our ſelues, that he would giue vs grace more and more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15947:37"/> and die to our owne works; and that he would ſtrengthen vs with grace more fully in all parts to obey him: ſo that we may increaſe like good trees, in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the fruites of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, till we feele not our ſelues, but Chriſt, thinking, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, working in vs. Thirdly, that he would <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> make vs perſeuer in his obedience to the end, and in the end. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that he would giue vs in all the euils we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, to make his will our will, and bleſſe his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15947:38"/> Name. Conſiderations mouing to the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout making of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to think how moſt liue in the open breach of all Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Would it not grieue a good ſubiect to ſee men trample downe the Kings lawes, and euery one runne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his owne head? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to thinke in how many things daily wee offend in our vnfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which maketh vs rather be vtterly idle, &amp; picke ſtrawes, then gird vp our ſelues to holy
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15947:38"/> thoughts? Our idle light diſcourſe, our inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections, our treſpaſſes euery where, &amp; following our owne luſts. Thirdly, how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly, and in a ſorrie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> faſhion, we performe our daily duties both towards God, and one another; what a deale of ſinne cleaueth to them, that we find not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things we deſire. Fourthly, our inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, which maketh vs no <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſooner in a good thing, but we are out againe: and as little birds leape
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15947:39"/> from pule to ſprigge, ſo we are out and in, and through ſloth cannot hold out at theſe works, which are a dead worke to our vnregenerate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> parts. Fiftly, our vtter impotencie to thinke, will, do, perfect (in ſome ſort) and perſeuer in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things; and the ſtrength of our naturall inclinations carying vs another way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, the manifold diſcomforts which the diuell doth muſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, that he might keepe vs from entring into, or continuing on,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15947:39"/> in any good action.</p>
                  <p>The concluſions are theſe:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that it is God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that giueth vs both will and deed, maketh vs perſeuer in euery good word and worke, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to profit in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Hoſ. 13. In me your fruite is found. Ioh. 15. Out of me you can do nothing. In thoughts and words we are like eckoes, we cannot ſpeak inwardly or outwardly till God hath ſpoken firſt to vs in the deeds we do: he prepareth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and worketh them firſt,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15947:40"/> we after him in nature, as a boy writing vnder one who leadeth his hand in that he writeth. For, longer then God acteth the grace we haue, it moueth not at all: for as an inſtrument now ſet in tune giueth no ſound if ſome Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian touch it not; ſo we when Gods kingdome coming hath diſpoſed vs by grace, and made vs fit to worke well, yet cannot worke any thing till God moueth vs vnto it, nor yet continue in working, longer then he vpholdeth vs in it. This
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15947:40"/> then is our ſanctuary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all our vnfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſobedience: hold the Lord who hath vndertaken to write his Law in thy heart, and to put his Spirit in thee, and make thee obey his commandement. And this muſt teach vs to giue all glorie to him, who is the firſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall worker of euery good thing in vs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we note <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> hence, that no mans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is perfect; for that we pray for is not yet attained. In many things we ſinne, in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15947:41"/> good things we do, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not perfect them: the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit a gainſt the fleſh, that we cannot do the things we would. Not that our deeds are ſinnes, but the beſt of them is ſinfull: As wine hauing ſome water mingled with it, yet is called wine; for the beſt part giueth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the whole. The Papiſts know not what it is truly to make this petition, that write ſo much for the iuſtice of workes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, note that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15947:41"/> Chriſtians muſt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues in any thing they haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but muſt ſtriue to perfection:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> Be ye perfect as your heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect. We muſt ſhoote at the higheſt marke, though we take our arrowes vp ſhort enough daily. When we call men ſtill on, they thinke wee know not what we would haue; do they not thus, and thus? &amp;c. but he that laboreth not to be better, will grow worſe and worſe, for who gathereth not, ſcattereth.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:15947:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, we ſee true Chriſtians muſt be as carefull to haue good liues, words, workes, &amp;c. as good hearts. We ſay not onely thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come, but thy will be done. Euery man will hope he hath grace in his heart, and yet no man careth for obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his life; but the not doers of Gods will deceiue themſelues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petition</hi> 4. <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words are eaſie all but the laſt <hi>[Bread;]</hi> it is put for whatſoeuer thing ſuſtaineth this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15947:42"/> preſent life and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it. <hi>Ionathan</hi> eating honie, is accounted to breake the oath of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bread. Daily bread is whatſoeuer is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for vs to poſſeſſe for the preſent; ſo giue of mercy to vs, and then renewing our faith and inuocation daily to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, who careſt for vs, all ſuch things which thou ſeeſt we may conueniently poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe for the preſent time. Firſt for thoſe who are Gods, but yet vncal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whether hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15947:43"/> the title of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or haue neither title nor poſſeſſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, (for many belonging to mercie conflict with extreame pouertie) we pray in the behalfe of theſe, that God would giue as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the one, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp; heires in Chriſt, the things they haue; for the other, that God would be pleaſed by a new grant, to furniſh them with neceſſaries, who haue iuſtly, as we all, forfeited all things. We who haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing about vs, yet find
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15947:43"/> want of others; we wiſh that God would ſupply vs ſo farre, as he ſeeth good for vs. We who are called, and haue for outward things more then we could in mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie aske, (for God doth for his ſometimes this way, and other, aboue that they can aske or thinke:) we do beg at God to maintaine theſe things vnto vs; for he muſt vphold our lot as well as deale vs forth our portion. Secondly, we wiſh that God would giue vs his leaue to vſe the things wee haue.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15947:44"/> Thirdly, that he would giue vs power to take a taſte of ſuch comforts which through his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, we haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of conſcience to vſe. Fourthly, that he would with his bleſſing make them comfortable to vs, ſo that we may with gladneſſe of heart vſe them. And from hence we may ſee that euery one hath reaſon to make this petition which ſhall be. Now if we be in Chriſt, and yet poore, hauing in a manner no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing, wee pray that God out of his ſecret
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15947:44"/> would miniſter to vs, &amp; make the fruite of his daily prouidence a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented portion vnto vs, be it neuer ſo little; and finally make vs ſee him by faith our all ſufficient God, that will not leaue vs, nor forſake vs. The motiues breeding deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions this way are, Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for all that find the want yet of ſomething, for the more comfortable ſeruice of God, that they would well weigh the wants of others and of themſelues. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> conſider what a ſweet thing it is, to feele this,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15947:45"/> that God or his grace giueth this or this to vs. If we ſit at boord with great perſonages, if they carue vs a bit and giue it vs, the whole feaſt is not ſo ſweete to vs, as their honorable remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of vs. All the creature is a deafe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut, and no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if God be not percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in it. Laſtly, that he would bleſſe all meanes we vſe, tending to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of this preſent life. Thirdly, for ſuch as haue abundance, they muſt conſider, how he that giueth theſe things is the maintainer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15947:45"/> how eaſily God might bring the things they haue to nothing, letting riotous ſeruants and children like back dores, bring downe the houſe. Secondly, how many wayes God can keepe them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being able to vſe or find comfort in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing they take or poſſeſſe; if he ſend a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into the conſcience touching the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, if he ſend ſickneſſe, deepe diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, lingering after that we haue not; or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if he ſhould giue vs to ſuch weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15947:46"/> in vſing any thing, that we ſhould breed our ſelues more bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the end, then we take comfort in the firſt taſting of them; how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle things put vs out, that for the time all we haue is nothing to vs? Laſtly, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how all things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods bleſſing are nothing, clothes warme not, meates nouriſh not, phyſicke heales not, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors proſper not to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any thing: which thoſe well know, whoſe falſe affia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced harts haue bene well whipped out
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15947:46"/> of all the creature. The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions follow. Firſt, that God giueth and maintaineth to vs all things belonging to this life. God giueth, God taketh, faith <hi>Iob.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> His bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing maketh rich, ſaith <hi>Salomon;</hi> Euery good &amp; perfect gift deſcendeth from him.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> Mine is all the earth, I giue it to whom I will: he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his hand and filleth euery liuing thing. For as in a houſe the Maiſter of the family keepeth (to the dogs) euery creature in it, giueth one greater another leſſer wages:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15947:47"/> putteth ſome in honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place, others in the ſcullerie: ſo doth God the great <hi>Pater familias,</hi> Father of all the family in heauen and in earth; neither can any deale vs a fit ſtate but he. For as the Phyſitian onely can preſcribe the diet, ſo God he ſeeth where a full and liberall meaſure, where a more ſparing is expedient. The diuell he taketh vpon him that all kingdomes are his, he giueth them as he will; a lowde lie; he cannot touch a hog till God ſealeth him a warrant:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15947:47"/> and as an executioner that killeth by poyſon, ſerueth the Magiſtrate: ſo doth he ſerue God in giuing a deadly ſweete poiſoned cup to thoſe God leaueth to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Againe, though our good, friends and our meanes helpe vs with this or that, yet God is the firſt donor; theſe are inſtruments conueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which God of grace deuiſeth to vs, and beſtoweth vpon vs. He that ſendeth a preſent is the giuer of it, not the man that putteth it into our hands; which doth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15947:48"/> teach vs to be content with that wee haue. We looke our children &amp; ſeruants ſhould take that of vs which we giue them, without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or diſcontented ſemblance, be it fine or courſe, &amp;c. How much more muſt we be willing to ſtand to Gods car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and not dare to quetch againſt his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it teacheth vs thankfulneſſe to him. If we ſoiourne a weeke or two with any, how thankfull are we? But we are Gods daily
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15947:48"/> gueſts al the yeare long: he layeth the cloath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where. The ſecond thing is, that the leaſt outward thing is the gift of Gods grace to vs; we deſerue it not, we are leſſe then the leaſt of his mercies, ſaith <hi>Iacob.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more free then gift, yea we aske it on gift, challenge it not as due. Theſe are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which God of his grace hath giuen me; ſuch therefore as will challenge heauen by forme of commutatiue iuſtice, becauſe they haue giuen a penny an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15947:49"/> to that penny worth, were neuer taught by the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, obſerue hence, that our faith and inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation muſt be daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed towards God for his care on vs in this life. Whatſoeuer we haue, our faith muſt be no leſſe on him, then if we were ſtripped naked of euery thing; yea our mouthes muſt be no leſſe open wide, to him. <hi>Dauid</hi> though a King, ſaith, The Lord is my potion, &amp; the ſuſtainer of my lot. Had we done
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15947:49"/> much for one, if he whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he felt himſelfe warme ſhould not reſpect vs, but looke at his owne ſtrength, would we not count it treachery? If a ſubſtantiall man, who deſerued credite alone, ſhould be leſſe truſted when he layeth downe a ſufficient pawne, would it be well taken? Apply this. But what need we euery day to do thus? Anſwer. Becauſe all we haue, God doth let vs no longer leaſes of it then for the day. Againe, this we haue of anothers; we cannot vſe it though we
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15947:50"/> haue it without the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners leaue; as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants that keepe things vnder vs, we allow them not without our leaues to do their pleaſure with them. Beſides you heard aboue, that God can keepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, or finding any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in them (though we vſe them) or feeling his ſweet grace, as who is the giuer of them. Wherefore let vs take heed of the ſenſuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the creature, and flie vp in ſpirit to him that giueth and maintaineth with vs all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15947:50"/> things; as the Sunne which both bringeth &amp; continueth the light with vs. Let vs not ſet downe our reſt vpon things preſent, and ſing with the glutton: Take thy reſt ſoule, or with the Prieſt: <hi>His requies mea;</hi> but by benefit of the things we haue, let vs, as by wings, flie vp higher into beleefe on our Creator. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore delighted in this, &amp; often to heare vs, doth keepe vs Tennants at will, as it were, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand to mouth often, that we might waite on him. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15947:51"/> had <hi>Nilus</hi> to water it, but the land of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites was to expect, the firſt and the latter raine, when God ſhould as a gardener with his ſpout pot, ſo from the bottels of the cloudes powre vpon them.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, obſerue that we muſt not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull cares for time to come: ſome are neuer well but while they haue things ſo fluſh, that they are not forced to go to God. Some though they haue neuer ſo much for the preſent,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15947:51"/> yet if they haue nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for times to come, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeeme to themſelues out of gun-ſhot, they are not contented. Hence it is that many rent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a ſunder with fore-caſting, and fearing, touching things to come: otherwiſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for time to come, which falleth within the reach of our daily courſe is not forbidden. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> laid vp in yeares of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt ſcarcitie. We are ſent to the Ant to ſchoole, that we may learne in Sommer to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15947:52"/> prouide againſt winter, and parents <hi>de iure</hi> do lay vp treaſures for their children: God would not haue vs ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Capuchians, who thinke it an offence to haue any thing vnſpent ouer night; nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane companions that ſing Care away, and ſet cocke on hoope, whoſe money burnes in their purſſes till it be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; nor yet fooliſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident ones who buy their fuell when it freeſeth; but care of time to come, which cometh from vnbeleefe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15947:52"/> to be greater then that we ſhould need to care.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, marke hence what he teacheth vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Bread which is neceſſary, and commonly begged for food. Marke hence that our deſire muſt be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate touching things of this preſent life. Thus <hi>Agur</hi> prayeth in the Prouerbs 30.8. Lord let me not want, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, feed me with food conuenient for me. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaith, Seeing thou giueſt me bread and rayment, thou ſhalt be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15947:53"/> my God for euer: <hi>Paul;</hi> Hauing bread and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let vs be content. Nature is content with ſmall things; and as a lampe with a litle oyle is maintained, with much extinguiſhed; ſo is this light, this naturall life which the ſoule cauſeth in the bodie. And it is to be marked; for not the hauing, but the louing, and affecting of great things is ſinfull. For, what God caſteth vpon vs walking within the compaſſe of our wayes, we are with thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to embrace it. A
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15947:53"/> mans proſperitie is not in abundance; for the dinne and tumult which accompanie the expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that follow vpon it, are more irkeſome then that exceeding of ones eſtate is contentfull. A moderate eſtate hath more eaſe and comfort, another more diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and oſtentation. Let vs therefore bridle in our inordinate appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, which know not how to ſay enough. If we haue but ſmal things let vs learne to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and deſire no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But how may we
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15947:54"/> know what is a lawfull from an vnlawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire? Euen as you know a thirſt naturall, from an vnnaturall thirſt, which a dropſie or ague cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; the one with a draught is ſo ſatisfied that another is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for: the other once ſerued, doth make way for freſh deſire after a ſecond: ſo theſe ſinfull ones, the enioying one, is but the beginning of another.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> 5. <hi>Petition: And forgiue vs, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This petition hath two thing to be marked.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15947:54"/> Firſt, the requeſt it ſelfe. Secondly, the inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. To forgiue a ſinne is to quit vs, and ſet vs free from the guilt and puniſhment, which by reaſon of ſinne we haue brought our ſelues into; and to accept of vs, and to vſe vs as if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had offended by our ſinnes: for ſinne maketh vs ſtand debtors to Gods iuſtice, indebted ſo farre as to ſatisfie by ſuffering deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. <hi>As we forgiue.</hi> Theſe words do not pleade a cauſe, vpon which God ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15947:55"/> vs; for we cannot loue, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent cannot forgiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, till God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen vs firſt: as the wall cannot reflect heate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ſtander by, till the Sunne hath ſhined vpon it. Neither do they make compariſon, in this wiſe, to forgiue me no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; but as thou ſeeſt me ready to forgiue another; as if our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe were a maſter ſampler or picture, after which God were to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his forgiuing of vs: but they do ſerue partly to inſinuate with
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15947:55"/> God by argument taken from the greater; We that haue much of the old leauen, by the ſparke of thy grace in vs, are ready to forgiue; be thou much more: or by holding forth a ſigne teſtifying of vs, that we are perſons to whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth forgiueneſſe, not ſhewing why wee ſhould be forgiuen: and thus ſtrengthening our faith to beleeue that we are heard in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly marke; we are ſaid to forgiue treſpaſſes againſt vs; for the ſinne
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15947:56"/> againſt God we cannot, but the iniurie or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage againſt our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we may; as if the Magiſtrate take a theefe wronging vs, we may forgiue him his iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mind towards vs, but cannot abſolue him from the offence againſt the law.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, we aske that God would apply that mercie of his, reaching to forgiueneſſe, vnto them that are yet the children of wrath, ouer whom yet his anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth through their vnbeleefe: and this we
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15947:56"/> aske in reſpect of our brethren by grace of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, yet vncalled.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for our ſelues, we do not aske that God would iuſtifie vs; for God is not off and on, he playeth not faſt and looſe. Whom once he iuſtifieth and forgiueth their ſinnes, he neuer remembreth ſinne againſt them. We therefore whoſe ſinnes he hath pardoned, aske three things; the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of his grace, that his mercifull pardon may be a gift without repentance. Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:15947:57"/> we aske the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, that he would make vs ſee and feele this forgiueneſſe of his; for our daily ſinnes do weaken our comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble apprehenſion, and dim the ſpirituall ſight of our ſoules, and do blot the counterpaine with vs of this releaſe God hath made vs. Now we get by this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition our releaſe newly exemplified, our ſight cleared, our ſence reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. To this ſecond branch therefore muſt be referred theſe three things as asked by vs.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15947:57"/> Firſt, that God would heale the doubtings and darkneſſe of our minds. Secondly, that he would ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our faith to ful aſſurance in this point, that our ſinnes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. Thirdly, that he would make vs feele our peace in the ioy follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we aske in this petition, that God would ſpare vs as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth his children, remouing from vs thoſe temporall chaſtiſements which our ſinnes might euery way bring vpon vs, to our great ſmart:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15947:58"/> for though God as a Iudge hath pardoned our ſinnes, yet as a father he may ſcourge them in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vs. The firſt meane of the more deuotionall propounding this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is, to let our hearts ſmite vs in the ſinnes which of infirmitie we we fall into; for becauſe men paſſe by ſinne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitently, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of it all the day, therefore they without life and power, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling deſire, propound this requeſt to God at <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> euening. Secondly, to marke how vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15947:58"/> it is when Gods countenance this way is hid from vs, and how heauie it is when dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and doubting do grow vpon vs.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we muſt get a feare of Gods fatherly corrections which we prouoke. The child that feareth the rod will be afraid and crie to haue a fault pardoned: So we muſt thinke what a ioy and ſweet ſtate it is to haue our <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by vs. Let vs then ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and affectionatly cry to our God, Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes. What
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15947:59"/> will a Malefactor now in danger leaue vnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to get his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don? what it one might be releaſed from his debt, but asking to haue it forgiuen? who would not ſeeke inſtantly, who would ſpare to ſpeake that haue this hope? The concluſions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, here is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that God onely can forgiue ſinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore the feeling of his grace to vs. No man can haue the life of God before iuſtification vnto
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15947:59"/> life on Gods part. Now contrition out of loue to God is a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life, and therefore muſt needs follow Gods pardon. This is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration againſt the Papiſts; none can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes but God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, againſt the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Papiſts note, that Gods forgiueneſſe is free; we do not redeeme it with our ſatisfactions, but beg it of mercie.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, marke that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> no man liueth without his daily ſinnes; we like infants haue our ſcapes; like wounded perſons
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15947:60"/> cured, our ſcarres, like white ſwans our blacke feete.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, that we may come to aſſurance that our ſinnes are forgiuen. For whatſoeuer we aske in Chriſt agreeable with his will, we know that we are heard in it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                     </label> They who beg a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſinne, are not ſure of pardon. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Falſe; for then Saint <hi>Peter</hi> who knew (by Papiſts confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) his ſinnes pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, could not ſay this prayer. Secondly, the conſtruction before, ſheweth, that the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15947:60"/> in forgiueneſſe, not the firſt beginning onely is here asked. We may inuert it; they who may aske forgiueneſſe may come to aſſurance that they haue it.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, marke that our faith and inuocation touching this point, muſt daily be renewed.</p>
                  <p>Out of the inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that our forgiuing others, is a ſigne we are ſuch to whom forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe belongeth, or a helpe ſtrengthening vs to beleeue the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſinnes, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue:</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:15947:61"/>
                  <p>All Gods actions to vs imprint their ſtampe in vs: his election ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs chuſe him, and chuſe the houſhold of faith before all others: Know, as the Apoſtle ſaith, according to the ſpirit, not the fleſh; his loue of vs maketh vs loue him and our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; his forgiuing vs maketh vs forgiue our brethren. Againe, when we find that a ſparke of grace maketh vs readie to forgiue; how much more may we aſſure our ſelues, that God will out of his endleſſe mercies
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:15947:61"/> be readie to forgiue vs? and this Act of ours though it is no cauſe, yet it is a condition, in which God doth make vs come to feele the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſinne which he freely forgiueth. So that as he who ſeeth a print of this or that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, doth know that the ſeale hath bene ſet there and applied: ſo wee feeling our ſelues readie to forgiue, do come to know this more ſurely, that Gods forgiueneſſe hath bene applyed in vs. And as one that doth ſee that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:15947:62"/> done which is greater, will eaſily beleeue the leſſer; ſo we ſeeing our ſelues made by his grace though ſinfull ones, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to forgiue, may much more be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that God ſo infinite in goodneſſe hath par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for vs, that we may feare him. Thirdly, as they who haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition on which a thing is to be done, may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect performance of that which depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on it; ſo we hauing forgiueneſſe, in which God hath promiſed vs forgiueneſſe, may be
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:15947:62"/> bold to aſſure our ſelues that we are pardoned.</p>
                  <p>Let vs therefore nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh this grace, and put away implacableneſſe, which once out, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returne; we ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue as neuer to forget: whereas Gods, and ſo all true forgiuing, is his neuer remembring any more that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Petition</hi> 6. <hi>And leade vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here are two things to be conſidered. The petition, the explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or correction an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:15947:63"/> to it. Petition, Leade vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; the explanation, But deliuer vs, &amp;c. that is, leade vs not ſo into temptation, but ſaue vs from the euill of it. We reade of three tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Firſt, Gods temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting man. Secondly, mans tempting God. Thirdly, the diuels temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting man. The firſt is two-fold, as when God manifeſteth his grace he hath beſtowed on man, and thus he tempted <hi>Abraham:</hi> or when he maketh man ſee his weakneſſe, and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:15947:63"/> he is to ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his grace. Man tempteth God, when leauing his ordinary way of waiting on God in meanes, he will put him to it, to ſhew his mercie, power, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his time. Thus the Iſraelites tempted him. But the third belongeth to this petition: the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels temptation, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth to bring vs into ſinne, and to with-draw vs from God to our temporall and eternall deſtruction. Euill here ſignifieth that which maketh vs worſe, not in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:15947:64"/> regard of our feeling onely, but in truth and before God: as which doth harmefully ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our vnion, or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our communion with God, who is our onely God and all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient portion. The ſumme is: O Lord we know it is to thy honor our life ſhould be a warfare, neither can we here liue without temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Do not ioyne vs againſt Sathan in battel, but ſo as ſtill to haue vs in remembrance, that whether he tempt vs by aduerſitie, or proſperity,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:15947:64"/> or what way ſoeuer, yet he may neuer ſeuer vs from thee, take vs out of thy hand, nor diminiſh the bleſſed communion we haue with thee, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then thou ſeeſt it needfull, to the end we might receiue it in great abundance. The things we aske are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that God would <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of his mercie keepe vs, from knowing tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo farre, as he may with his glory; not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the diuell to aſſaile vs this way, much leſſe preuaile againſt vs: for though we cannot ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:15947:65"/> make this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, yet vnder the Lords correction, and with condition it may be propounded; If it be poſſible, let that cup paſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly we deſire, that if we needs muſt conflict, that yet God would vphold vs and make vs ſuperiors; euen conquerors in euery thing, wherein we are to be tempted. Now this we do not aske ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, for ſometimes it is good that we ſhould be foiled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we deſire in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:15947:65"/> this petition, that God, if he ſee it good ſo to humble vs, as to let vs take the fall, yet he would not let our faith faile finally; but would ſo ſtrengthen vs, that we may ſee all the euils that we haue ſuffered wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to our good, and our ſelues at length more then conquerors, in him who loueth vs.</p>
                  <p>Finally, as we aske <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> this preſently for our ſelues who are alreadie in this warfare, ſo we wiſh it to all Gods elect when they ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the like condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:15947:66"/> Now the motiues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to thinke to what the temptations of the diuell tend: this is the white he ſhooteth at, that he might make vs naked before God; ſtripped of his fauour, which is better then life. For the diuell ſeeketh by them to make vs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor God, rob our hearts of his kingdome, ſetter vs ſo with our ſin, that we may be diſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled from obeying him; to take away all our peace and proſperity in things outward, to fill vs with feare and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:15947:66"/> in all the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we go about, and vncomfortable doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, yea deſpairings touching the pardon of ſinne; in a word, to bereaue vs of all good which in the former pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions we deſire; and to bring vpon vs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary euils which are moſt horrible. He play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſmall games when he beginneth his temptations. Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> we muſt remember how tedious his former tempting &amp; preuailing againſt vs hath bene; for we (like children, who
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:15947:67"/> remember beating no longer then it ſmarteth) we I ſay, remember the bitterneſſe of our daily falls the diuell giueth vs, no longer then God let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſting of them ſtick in vs; and this doth make vs that we feeling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot pray againſt that whoſe anguiſh and euill we do not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we muſt conſider, how we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where ſubiect to temptations, at home, abroad, in wife, children, ſeruants; in good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, to ſecuritie and vnfruitfulneſſe; in bad,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:15947:67"/> yea in good deeds; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we do them, when we haue done them: as to ſecuritie and pride af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at bed, at board. For as fooles and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not knowing euils feare them not, ſo we not knowing this euill, are leſſe fearefull, and flee not ſo fearingly, praying to haue it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented; euery where ſnares of temptation are laid for vs. Who that ſhould go ſuch a way, in which he could not take a ſtep without danger, would not go warily, and often lift vp his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:15947:68"/> heart for protection? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, we muſt think how diligent and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the diuel is; he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what baites we bite at, and will caſt them out euery where: he knoweth where we are weakeſt, and he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer want occaſions to prouoke vs. Againe, we muſt thinke how migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he is, what can he not do with vs if God keepe vs not? he would carrie vs to any euill, as a whirlwind doth the dry <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ſtubble. Fiftly, we muſt often repent our owne infirmities, how we be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:15947:68"/> ſo farre from being able to withſtand him, that all we haue of our owne, is readier to follow then he to whiſtle vs after him. Sixtly, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſuch examples of worthies as haue bene grieuouſly foiled; as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Peter,</hi> &amp;c. Yea preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents we haue of ſome hanging themſelues, ſome tempted to it; for ſuch examples are like the thunder, though it ſtriketh a few, it feareth all: and are not we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to haue our minds diſtracted, aſſaulted, with any euen the moſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:15947:69"/> grieuous things that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we heard to haue befallen others?</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a ioy it is when we go a day more freed. Lord what an eaſe is it to the ſoule? or if we be in a litle forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſinne, yet if we be reſcued ſeaſonably, how doth it reioyce vs? what peace doth it ſpeake to vs? Looke 1. Sam. 25.32. Now could we worke vpon our hearts the feeling of this benefit when he haue it, the ſweetneſſe of it would enforce vs to beg
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:15947:69"/> it heartily; whereas not heeding the worth of it, we aske it vnaffectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly. Now follow the concluſions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, this petition <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> compared with the 1. Cor. 10. about the 13. God will not ſuffer you to be tempted: we ſee how that Gods ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood without his action, he is a voluntary agent in theſe things which he ſuffereth. We muſt not thinke his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is a pure permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, either without his will, or working in the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:15947:70"/> thing permitted, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mans is; for man may be ſaid partly to ſuffer this, not to do it, becauſe other cauſes haue their actiuity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie on him; but it is otherwiſe with God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, obſerue that God doth leade vs into all our temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is ſaid, Math. 4. Chriſt was carried of the Spirit to be tempted. God is the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he onely when he ſeeth meete doth bring his champions forth, and letteth the power of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:15947:70"/> darkneſſe encounter them; neither can the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels ſtirre, neither we bid battell of our ſelues. Can the Lions ſtirre till the keeper bring them out? can a dog runne till he that hath him in a leaſſe looſe him? So it is, God he hath them chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in his almightie power, yea throwne downe to the priſon of hell: farther then he doth looſe them, and bring them into the earth, where this ſhew is repreſented, and battell to be ſeene, they are not able to do any
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:15947:71"/> thing. Againe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not on the other ſide, being ſet vpon, buckle with the aduerſarie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer till God doth leade vs to it. The Kings champion is not to play at his owne pleaſure, no more are we farther then God deſigneth it. But how can God leade vs into thoſe temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he ſeeth will certainly bring vs into ſinne? Anſwer. Becauſe ſinne it ſelfe is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely euill, but onely in reſpect of man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, who would in ſo doing peruert the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:15947:71"/> order, though he is vnable; as who accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſheth Gods will, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth contrary it, for ought he knoweth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as vipers are euill ſubſtances, or natures, which yet are good to that art which maketh vipers of them; or any poiſon which is euill, as it is poiſon in it ſelfe conſidered, yet is good as it is poiſon, to a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full phyſitian: and as a bliſter on the fleſh is a naturall euill as a bliſter, yet a bliſter as a bliſter is good when a cunning phyſitian doth draw it,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:15947:72"/> and may ſee it for good vſe; ſo is ſin to God: we muſt then not caſt our ſelues into temptation; he that loueth danger ſhall periſh. We muſt not make our ſelues poore as thoſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritickes that renounce all their ſubſtance, that in voluntary pouertie they may commend themſelues to God. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this muſt teach vs contentment in all our temptations: not that we muſt preuent repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but we muſt when we are truly humbled by
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:15947:72"/> this meanes, keepe our ſelues from being ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp of ſorrow. For Gods will, and Gods turning all to good; the diuell will whiſper them ſo as to make vs paſſe by all exerciſe of a broken ſpirit in thoſe things wherein we haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, from this conſideration we muſt walke in feare before our God, who as a ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſetteth his dog on a ſtray ſheepe, ſo can he ſet the diuell on vs to hound vs home if we ſtray from him. Laſtly,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:15947:73"/> we ſee from this to our comfort, that the diuell cannot come againſt vs at his pleaſure; we are in the hands of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father. Thirdly, we note hence, that all our ſtrength againſt temptation is in God onely; he onely diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the workes of the diuell, trampleth Sathan vnder feete, keepeth him that he cannot ſo much as be diſturbant to vs; when it pleaſeth him we are downe with the leaſt blaſt; were we in ſtate of innocencie we would not ſtand a moment: let
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:15947:73"/> vs therefore truſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly on his grace, put on the ſhield of faith onely. Our forefathers acknowledged y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, not their ſtrength, gaue them all ſaluation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt corporall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; how much more muſt we confeſſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſpirituall? Who knoweth the power of Sathan, or the infirmity of their owne fleſh, that will not confeſſe this moſt entirely? But what ſerueth the armour for? Anſwer. Onely to this end, that we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to get and hold God
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:15947:74"/> with vs, fighting for vs. Fourthly, we ſee hence, not temptations, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of them is ſimply to be prayed againſt; for theſe are often moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall. We muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learne to yeeld o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and bid our God ſmell a ſacrifice from the bittereſt things we taſte, ſo farre as they are his diſpoſition; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhame to our ſelues in them, as they are the fruits of follie.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, we may note hence, that no tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be able total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or finally to ſeparate
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:15947:74"/> the Saints from God; for that we are taught to pray agreeable with his will, we are heard in that. Now this were the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt euill, not onely in regard of our ſeeming or appearance to vs, but of the matter it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, this is a great daily mercie, when God keepeth vs from temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: not to know a diſeaſe is better, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to be healed of it; indeed Gods men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is better then his making, which ſomwhat alters the matter. Not to fall when we are readie
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:15947:75"/> to fall, is a great fauour. If one when our feete are ready to fall from vs, ſhould hold vs vp, we would count it a great benefit; but to haue our damages aduantage vs, this is the euidence of power and goodneſſe it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The concluſion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, partly contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a reaſon why wee aske all theſe things at Gods hands; partly a confirmation of faith asking; partly a praiſing of God. From which, three things are to be marked. Firſt, that none
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:15947:75"/> is to be inuocated on, but he who hath the kingdome, power and glorie: therfore no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words then containe the reaſon, why we come petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to our heauenly Father. For as one lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this or that in a houſe which is the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, cometh in by the backe doore, if he pray a ſeruant to giue it him whoſe it is not, who hath no power ſo to do, &amp;c: ſo if we ſeeke our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities temporall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, at Angels or
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:15947:76"/> Saints, which are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to God, who haue no power to do any thing farther then bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to by God, we take a wrong way to the wood.</p>
                  <p>But the Papiſts thinke all is made whole while they do call vpon Saints or Angels, not as the principall authors of the things they aske, but as ſecondary patrons, who vnder God worke theſe things for vs. To which is anſwered, that not onely to do religious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration in any kind to them, as the principall
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:15947:76"/> and chiefe power, is ſin: but alſo to call on them, or truſt in them, as being ſome ſecondarie diuine powers, although infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to God. The Angel-worſhip among the Coloſſians, did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thus much, as if they had bene the chiefe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine powers; and yet is condemned. <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> did not enact that he ſhould be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as the higheſt God; yet becauſe he would haue honour, in ſome degree diuine, <hi>Daniel</hi> did decline it as flat ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie. Againe, this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:15947:77"/> with which they would ſalue their fact, may be turned vpon them, as making againſt themſelues. For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe may not be called vpon, neither may be truſted to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, becauſe they are ſecondarie workers of things vnder God who is the principall agent.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we ſee what may confirme vs in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope to receiue our requeſts, namely, to thinke that God hath the kingdome ouer vs, that he is powerfull and glorious. There is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:15947:77"/> betweene Kings and their people, which bindeth them mutually one to another. Hence it is that we promiſe our ſelues protection, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in our life, the benefit of ſubiects from them, becauſe we are their ſubiects, and they haue the kingdome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs. That God who by reaſon of this obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſinful men to ſeeke the weale of all their people, becauſe they haue receiued a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ouer them; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will not faile on the ſame ground, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:15947:78"/> all good to vs, who liue vnder the regiment of his grace. Yet becauſe it is not enough that God ſhould haue the regall authoritie ouer vs, vnleſſe he had the power alſo of working all things for our weale, therefore this is ioyned [Thine is the power.] What were ſubiects the better to be vnder a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prince, but weake, hauing as ſhort hands to do them good, as a large heart to wiſh it them? So ſhould it fare betwixt God and vs, if he were not almighty,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:15947:78"/> able to ſubdue all things to himſelfe; our faith were ſhaken. For we cannot expect the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Sathan vnder our feete, the quickning of vs in our ſoules to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good worke, the iuſtifying, the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of vs; we cannot expect theſe things from one who hath not all power.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, had God the right to helpe vs, had he the power alſo; yet were it a thing that made not for his glorie, reſpected not the aduancement of his honor, our beleefe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:15947:79"/> might wauer: which now it need not do, it being Gods honour to performe all good things for his choſen. Honor is with men the ſpurre of actions: haue men right and power to effect this or that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce not to their honor and glorie, they will not moue a finger to it. But now there is nothing that wanteth to our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, while we know that we are ſuch to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath right; ſuch for whom he hath all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; ſuch, whom to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:15947:79"/> and bleſſe with all things ſpiritual and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, is his great glory. The caſe ſtanding thus, how can we doubt of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the things we aske at his hand in the Name of his Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>Amen] True it is; we thus flie to thee, ô Lord, be it according to our deſire. An aſſeueration, wiſh, or expreſſing of earneſt longing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all the things in this prayer aboue named.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15947:80"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15947:80"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A TREATISE VPON THE SIXE PRINCIPLES:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Written by that faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God, Maiſter <hi>PAVL BAINE,</hi> ſometime Preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Richard Field <hi>for</hi> Robert Milbourne. <hi>1619.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15947:81"/>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:15947:81"/>
                  <div n="1" type="principle">
                     <head>THE FIRST PRINCIPLE.</head>
                     <p>Queſtion. <hi>VVHat doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue concerning God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Anſw. <hi>There is one God, Creator and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of all things, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All neceſſary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which man is bound to know, may be reduced to two heads; The knowledg of God,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:15947:82"/> Iohn 17.1. This is life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, to know God; and the knowledge of himſelfe, heathens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging their <hi>noſſe teipſum,</hi> the chiefeſt wiſedome. Now the knowledge of God is firſt in order, as who is the firſt ſampler after which man was created (for we were made after his likeneſſe,) as alſo in whoſe affectionate knowledge the bliſſe of the creature conſiſteth. Concerning God three things are ſet downe to be beleeued: firſt, the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of his diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:15947:82"/> ſecondly, his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or working with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelfe: thirdly, his diſtinction of perſons. For the firſt: beſide the euident teſtimonies of Scripture, on which our faith is builded, we may by reaſon demonſtrate this truth. Firſt to vnfold it, then to prooue it. God is one not in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and kind, in which regard all men may be ſaid one: nor in conſent, as the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of beleeuers were ſaid one, Act. 4. But one in nature, the ſpirituall eſſence of God which is
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:15947:83"/> eternall, knowing all things, paſt, preſent, and to come; almightie, &amp;c. being but one, and no more in number: as this elementary lightſome body of the Sunne is but one, ſo that ſpirituall nature of God, which is a light to which is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, is but one ſingular nature, which is not nor cannot be multiplied. Sound reaſon teacheth that God is infinitly perfect aboue all that man can imagine; but were there many gods that had euery one ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally their diuine nature,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:15947:83"/> as there are many men and Angels, that haue ſeuerally their diſtinct, humane, and angelicall natures in them; then we might conceiue a more perfect God then any, viz. ſuch a one as had in himſelfe the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the other. This therefore doth teach vs how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; not as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens did, who thought it multiplied as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of other creatures, but as of one ſingular eſſence, which admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not any other by it,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:15947:84"/> as hauing it in ſelfe all perfection which can be found in the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Secondly, we ſee hence the incomparable vnity which the Father, Sonne, and Spirit haue; as who haue euery one the ſelfe ſame nature. To this we muſt looke, that we may in our owne meaſure expreſſe it in being of one heart, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and affecting the ſame things. Father, I pray thee that as thou and I are one, ſo theſe may be one, one myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſon.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond thing is
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:15947:84"/> his working without himſelfe, that is, his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary bringing forth the whole creature viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inuiſible, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and being different from his owne. For as man and woman do ſome works within their owne nature, as propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating their like; ſome without, as build houſes, make other artificiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices: ſo God hath his worke within his diuine nature, as the eternall begetting of his Sonne, &amp; breathing of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; as alſo his workes without his nature, ſuch
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:15947:85"/> as he doth voluntarily of his owne accord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing had libertie of will not to haue made them, or otherwiſe to haue framed them then they are. Now firſt he is ſaid the Creator, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth two things: Firſt, his giuing a being to all theſe things we ſee, and to all ſpirituall natures which are not ſeene with the eye, when they were not at all in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things. Nothing can make it ſelfe: and therfore as ſeeing good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buildings in cities peopled, we gather that
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:15947:85"/> there were excellent workmen; ſo beholding this earthly habitation with the furniture of it, we may conclude, there was ſome moſt wiſe and mighty Spirit that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med theſe things. The ſecond thing in creating is, that God doth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the kinds of things, and vphold the being which he giueth them. For nothing that is not this or that by nature, can longer continue to be ſo, then the working of the cauſe laſteth which firſt brought it to be ſo. As water is not
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:15947:86"/> hote by nature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore longer then fire is vnder, which firſt made it warme, it will not continue in heate, but by little and little draw to coldneſſe. So the aire is darke, and therefore as the Sunne maketh light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome day, ſo longer then it abideth, the day laſteth not. So things not hauing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues their being, kinds, law of propagation, but receiuing theſe things from God; longer then he vpholdeth them in this eſtate they could not endure, but would
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:15947:86"/> returne to nothing, whence they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. A man when he hath made an houſe, doth leaue it, &amp; it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth without him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he giueth an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall order onely, not the ſubſtantiall being, which the matter of the building hath in it ſelfe, not from the builder. But did man giue the being eſſentiall as well as order artificiall, were he withdrawne, the whole frame would be diſſolued; as if he ſtirre any thing that moueth not of it ſelfe, where his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:15947:87"/> motion ſtayeth, the thing ſo mooued doth ſtay likewiſe. Secondly it is ſaid, the Gouernor, that is, he moueth them to ſuch ends as are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him. A wiſe houſholder ordereth his whole familie. A wiſe King keeping in his Court, doth by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and lawes rule the remoteſt parts of his countrey. So God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the family in heauen or earth, King &amp; Lord of all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; he in the heauens which is the court of his Maieſtie, doth by his
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:15947:87"/> power, lawes, Spirit of grace, rule heauen, earth, hell; for hell is but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the great God. But how fareth it then that ſuch wicknedneſſes are committed? Anſwer. There is nothing ſimply euill, but onely in regard of the inferiour inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who is willing, but not able to peruert the diuine order; and therefore theſe euils we ſee are like two faced pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, which ſeeme on one ſide beautifull wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, on the other vglie monſters. So looke at the lewdeſt workes, as
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:15947:88"/> from God they are moſt beautifull, as from the ſinner monſtrous; as in the crucifying of Chriſt the curſed Iew wrought deſpitefully, but God moſt graciouſly. <hi>Ob.</hi> He that is a Creator &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he was not, is changed; but God now is thus, and before the world began he was not, and therefore he is changed. The firſt part is falſe, becauſe the termes of Creator, and gouernor, put no reall change inherent in God, but imply a chang
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:15947:88"/> in the creature. For as the Sunne enlighteneth the earth euery day, and changeth the face of the creatures, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe changed; ſo God createth and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth. <hi>Vſes.</hi> Firſt, we ſee here a ground of thankfulneſſe to God; we count an vnthankfull child a monſter of men, becauſe he is vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to them by whom he receiued his being; but how much more groſſe is our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God, whoſe inſtruments onely our parents were in bringing
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:15947:89"/> vs forth. Secondly, we ſee hence what cauſe we haue to walke in feare: for we moue, haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, liue in him. If one ſhould haue vs ſo ouer a riuer, that if his hold ſhould ceaſſe we could not but drowne forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; ô how would we feare to prouoke him who had vs at ſuch van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? but thus it is with God, that if his power vphold not, we ſhould come forthwith to vtter nothing. Thirdly, we ſee what a leud part it is, not to acknowledge God. Not to acknowledge a
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:15947:89"/> King in his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea not to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to take the oath of allegiance, we diſclaime it in any as a part vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a ſubiect; ſo not to ſubiect our ſelues to the liuing God, is a part vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie any creature.</p>
                     <p>The laſt thing to be beleeued is the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this one God, in regard of perſons, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt; for the conceiuing whereof foure things are to be noted. Firſt, that theſe reſpects of God, beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, begotten, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:15947:90"/> do not make any compoſition as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers eſſentiall parts of one thing, but diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction onely; as Eaſt, Weſt, North, South, ſo diſtinguiſh the heauens, that they are not eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts whereof they are compounded. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that theſe three, though there is order of precedency in nature, as the Father before the Sonne, the Sonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spirit, yet they are all coeternal in time; as fire is in naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration before heate
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:15947:90"/> or light, yet in time they are altogether. Thirdly, it is to be noted, that there are ſaid three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not three Gods: for neither <hi>tres dij,</hi> nor <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Deus</hi> are fitly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, becauſe the one multiplieth, at leaſt in appearance, the diuine eſſence; the other reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the diuine ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Three perſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are, hauing all one and the ſame diuine nature, as if <hi>Thomas, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Mathew</hi> could be ſuppoſed to haue one ſingular ſoule and body common to them
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:15947:91"/> all, &amp; entirely poſſeſſed of euery one. Fourthly, we muſt know that no carnall thing is to be thought of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, natiuitie, proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but the myſterie is altogether ſpiritually to be conceiued; but this myſterie is in regard of clearer knowledge, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, till we ſhall be like Angels. In the meane while <hi>aſpici poteſt, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpici non poteſt,</hi> leſt that befall vs which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to them that looke full againſt the Sunne, viz. leſt our eyes be da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="principle">
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:15947:91"/>
                     <head>The ſecond Principle.</head>
                     <p>Q. <hi>VVHat doſt thou beleeue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Man, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thine owne ſelfe?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Anſw. <hi>All men are wholly corrupted through Adams fall, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſlaues of Sathan, and guilty of eternall condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The knowledge of man followeth, which ſtandeth in theſe foure points: Firſt, to know how he was in his ſtate of creation; which is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer, and is left to be
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:15947:92"/> gathered by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Secondly, what is his eſtate as he is fallen. Thirdly, what by grace. Fourthly, what it ſhall be in glorie. The three laſt are opened in this, and the queſtions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. The ſecond eſtate this anſwer vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſetting downe our miſerie, firſt in reſpect of our corruption; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in reſpect of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The corruption is ſet downe by three cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, firſt from the parties corrupted, all; ſecondly from the quantity of it, wholly;
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:15947:92"/> thirdly from the firſt author of it, <hi>Adams fall.</hi> The latter of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hath two branches. Firſt, our thraldome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sathan. Secondly, our guilt of damnation euerlaſting. Firſt then it is to be marked, that no creature coming of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> is exempted from corruption. Rom. 5. In whom all haue ſinned: We, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh people, are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the children of wrath as well as others. For like as the roote, like will be the branches, and who can bring any
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:15947:93"/> thing cleane from that which is vncleane? So that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is not exempted, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was conceiued, nor yet liued without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; who was more bleſſed in beleeuing on God her Sauiour, then in bearing his fleſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her belly. Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was free. For though he was in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> loynes, yet he was not of <hi>Adam,</hi> but mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly framed by the holy Ghoſt; and ſo, as he was exempted from the ordinary line of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, ſo likewiſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="177" facs="tcp:15947:93"/> the corruption which was a conſequent of it. Secondly, it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that we are not in part, but wholly corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there is nothing in vs ſincere and vndefiled. So that looke as a man who hath a leproſie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergrowing him from top to toe, ſo are wee: The imagination of mans heart is euill, yea onely euill continually. Gen. 6.5. &amp; 8.21. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs voide of all ſtrength to good. Rom. 5.10. We cannot thinke a thought as of our
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:15947:94"/> ſelues. Nay, full of enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Rom. 8. The wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie againſt God: prone to all euill. Rom. 3. We are, in a word, dead in ſinne and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes. Eph. 2. Which doth let vs ſee how the Papiſt is deceiued, who dreameth of a power in the will vnto good, if it be looſed &amp; awakened; as in a man aſleepe, or fettered, there is power to go, and ſo forth, if he be waked and ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. But the life of God, in which all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:15947:94"/> vnto good was grounded, is gone from vs. Epheſ. 4. They were eſtranged from the life of God through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: now twixt them and vs by nature there is no difference. <hi>Ob.</hi> Man hath by nature ſome knowledge of God, and his dutie to God and man. <hi>Anſw.</hi> None at all that is true and ſauing, but ſuch as may ſhew the ruines of time in him, &amp; make him more inexcuſable. Secondly, we muſt labour to haue conſcience of this our total defilement: I know
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:15947:95"/> in me there dwelleth no good thing: for it hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth vs, and maketh vs haue no confidence in the fleſh, but haue all our reioycing in Chriſt Ieſus; and know that what good thing we do, it is in him and through him. The third thing to be marked is, that ſinne wherewith our nature is defiled, is as a loathſome corruption in it: it is the death of the ſoule which maketh it rot in filthie qualities, as odious be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, as the ſtinke and filthie ſauour of a dead corps is in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:15947:95"/> of man. Yea it doth putrifie the body and make it mortall, fretting it through, often before it be diſcerned, as a moth doth a garment: which muſt the more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vs. Were we with <hi>Iob</hi> from top to toe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with biles, it would grieue vs: but our whole ſpirits being fraught with more filthie cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out at the eye, mouth, eare, &amp;c. we are not touched.</p>
                     <p>The fourth thing, through <hi>Adam,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs whence our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:15947:96"/> is deriued, euen from our firſt parent, whoſe ſinne we are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of, and whoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is propagated vnto all his poſteritie. For if parents rebelling againſt earthly Princes, their children are tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſinherited, much more is this iuſt with God. And as we haue the guilt of his fault, ſo we cannot be free from his infection: <hi>Parentem proles ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> Like egge, like bird; as often men hauing the falling ſickneſſe, and be get children hauing the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:15947:96"/> ſame diſeaſes; which muſt make vs further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile our condition. Were we deſcended of one that had bene exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for treaſon, and ſo were pointed at as a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous brood, without inheritance in earth; had we but with our nature the ſtone, or falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from our next pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, we would bewaile our vnhappy natiuities. The ſecond part of our miſery firſt teacheth vs, that all of vs by nature are ſlaues of Sathan. To be a ſlaue or vaſſall is hard, but to be the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:15947:97"/> vaſſals moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hence it is we are ſaid to be in his power, and in the kingdome of darkneſſe, and he to be the god of this world. For looke as a man is ſeruant to whom he yeeldeth himſelfe volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily to obey, ſo are we, as who reuolting from God haue voluntarily enthralled our ſelues to Sathan. For as the ſoule leauing the body, the body dieth, ſo God lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſoule, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the preſence of power but of grace, the ſoule forthwith dieth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:15947:97"/> as a iailour hath from the King &amp; chiefe Iuſticer power ouer his priſoners, ſo hath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than as being iaylour &amp; executioner to Gods iuſtice, power ouer vs; which muſt make vs ſtill ſee our miſerie. Woe to the ſheepe whom the wolfe gouerns: were we ſlaues ſeruing vnder the Turke in his gallies, how would it grieue vs? but thus one might be more free then the Turke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Were we as the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in Egypt, wee would lament: but to be thralled to him that like
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:15947:98"/> a roaring Lion ſeeketh to deuoure vs, is much more intollerable. Laſtly marke that we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to eternall death, death endleſſe and eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, both of ſoule and body; the ſoule is dead, while we liue we feele it not, becauſe wee are dead: the body is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall tending to death, for as a moth is in a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo lieth ſin in vs, corrupting our body by little and little without ceaſſing, till it be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. In death the ſoule is gathered to thoſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſpirits, who keepe
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:15947:98"/> it impriſoned in hell till iudgement; then at the great day ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, hauing ſinned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhall ſuffer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euerlaſtingly. If a man ſinne againſt the maieſty of an earthly mortall Prince, he is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with temporary death or perpetuall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, if he could be ſuppoſed to liue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, he ſhould lie in for euer; how much more deſeruedly are we ſubiect to eternall death who haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an eternall God? Which ſtill moueth vs
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:15947:99"/> to take notice of our eſtates, and lament them while there is hope. If our bodies were in ſuch caſe, threatning death, would we not be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched? if we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die as male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, would we not wring our hands to thinke on ſuch miſerie? How much more ſhold it mooue vs to thinke that we are ſubiect to euerlaſting death, which hath already ſeized vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs in the ſpirituall death of our ſoules, and mortalitie or dying ſtates of our bodies?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="principle">
                     <pb n="189" facs="tcp:15947:99"/>
                     <head>The third Principle.</head>
                     <p>Q. <hi>VVHat meanes is there for thee to eſcape this damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Anſw. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made Man, by his death vpon the Croſſe, &amp; by his righteouſneſſe, hath perfectly alone by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, accompliſhed all things that are needfull for the ſaluation of man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The anſwer ſetteth downe two things, firſt, the author of ſaluation, ſecondly his perfect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of vs. In the firſt
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:15947:100"/> there are two things, firſt who it is, viz. Ieſus Chriſt: ſecondly what kind of perſon he is, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort compounded, viz. the eternall Sonne of God, God with the Father and Spirit; and man alſo, that is, God the Sonne hauing ſuch a ſoule and body, as we haue for the eſſentiall nature of them, aſſumed to him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fellowſhip of his perſon. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, his perfect ſauing of vs, is likewiſe ſet downe, firſt from his actiue obedience, that is, his fulfilling the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:15947:100"/> of all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; and his paſſiue obedience, that is, bearing the curſed death, which are the things whereby our-ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is wrought for vs: Secondly, from the ſolitary manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king theſe things, viz. that he did and ſuffered all things due to this end, by himſelfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leauing part of this buſineſſe to the Saints and our ſelues. Firſt, for his Name: ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to great perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they know their names and their whole
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:15947:101"/> ſtyle; which comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all their Signiories, honours, and offices which they haue and beare in the common wealth; and we, if wee heare of ſome perſon more famous for this or that, are not well till we haue learned his name: how much more ſhould we be affected toward the name of him, that hath wrought the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind? Now as great men haue their proper names and ſtyles of office, honour, &amp;c: ſo Chriſt hath his proper name Ieſus, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:15947:101"/> a Sauiour; and of office, Chriſt, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth one annointed. Names ſhould admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature of things named by them: ſo do theſe names. For he was called Ieſus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was to ſaue his people from their ſins, not only from the guilt, which he doth when he bringeth vs to ſee in him the pardon of our ſins; but from the power of ſinne: which he doth euery day, yea houre, while he tameth &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth our ſinne in vs,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:15947:102"/> preſerueth vs from the rage of it, and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the occaſions wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it would ſwell and rage in vs, and trampleth Sathan vnder our feete, who is the vnquiet moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of ſinne in vs, and muſterer of all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt vs. Now he is the Chriſt, or annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God; becauſe that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts &amp; kings annointing did ſignifie, is accompliſhed in him, in whoſe humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture God dwelleth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally; adorning it with innumerable gifts of grace and glory ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall;
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:15947:102"/> as the ſoule doth bring forth in the body many naturall properties, while it abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth therein as perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally conioyned with it: and thus he was annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that he might be a fit King and Prieſt, and Prophet to his Iſrael. How ſweete then are theſe names of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, ſo refreſhing the heart as a ſweete oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth the ſenſes! they are <hi>mel in ore, melos in aure, iubilum in corde.</hi> We muſt therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after them &amp; glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know them. He were
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:15947:103"/> a ſorrie ſeruant that ſhould not care to know his maiſters name to whom he belongeth. What ſhall become of vs, who, profeſſing our ſelues to belong to God our Sauiour, know not the firſt letter of his name?</p>
                     <p>Secondly, marke what kind of perſon our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour is, ſuch a one who is the eternall Sonne of God made man, that is, God and man in one perſon; the eternall Son being a perfect perſon from all eternitie, taking our nature into the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:15947:103"/> of his owne perſon. To open it, firſt note who is incarnate, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Sonne; then how. To the firſt, we are ſons but by grace and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, begotten in time by the preaching of the Goſpell. The Angels, &amp; <hi>Adam</hi> in innocencie were called ſonnes, but in time brought forth of nothing, viz. when time began: but Chriſt is begotten of the ſelfe-ſame ſpirituall eſſence the Father hath, coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with himſelfe. Now to know how they are vnited, we muſt conſider
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:15947:104"/> that the three perſons of the Trinitie are one, but in nature which is one and the ſelfe ſame in all the three; but here two natures are vnited in one perſon, God the Sonne hauing a perfect perſonall being, did take a ſoule and body, not into vnion of his diuine nature, but into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his perſon. So that the nature di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and humane are diſtinct, but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall being, which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before ſubſiſted in the nature of God, doth now ſubſiſt in the nature
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:15947:104"/> of man, which doth no leſſe eſſentially belong to the Sonne of God his perſon, then the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature it ſelfe, in which before it onely ſubſiſted. The ſumme is, God the Sonne from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting a perfect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, being onely in the nature of God, did in his time appointed, create a ſoule and body, not hauing perſonall being of themſelues within his owne perſon; that his perſonall being might as really exiſt afterward for euer in mans nature, with the diuine, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:15947:105"/> it had done in the diuine nature alone. So that as the ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy make vp the perſonal being of one man, ſo the diuine nature and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane are one Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort. This is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, the ſoule hath no perfect perſonall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelfe before the body, but the ſoule as one part, and the body as another, do mutually conſpire in conſtituting the perſonall being: a third thing, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath by it ſelfe. Whereas God the Son, doth not take our nature
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:15947:105"/> as to make vp a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall being, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; but to receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, hauing perfect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that which it ſelfe had not. So that our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a part of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not conſtituting any perfection in it, but ſuperadded to it, as in it ſelfe moſt perfect from euerlaſting to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. This compariſon ſhall ſerue; for others of the oake and miſceltoe, of a ſience engraffed into a tree, are not more plaine in expreſſing, how the two natures of
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:15947:106"/> God-man become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall parts, as it were of one perſon: and all ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes here muſt needs be defectiue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is nothing in nature that hath the eſſence and ſubſtance of any thing without the being this or that thing; as Chriſts ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die were the common nature and ſubſtance of a man, without being this or that man. Againe there is nothing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which being this or that, can communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that being it hath with another, as the
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:15947:106"/> Sonne of God doth his perſonall ſubſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with this body and ſoule, which were alwaies without any being but in him. Our great Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our then is God-man. Were be not man, he could not die, nor haue right to redeeme vs, as being not our kinſman, with many ſuch like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: were he not God, his obedience and ſufferings wold not be of value: God hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs with his bloud. Againe, man could not ſuſtaine the curſe, and thoſe powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:15947:107"/> fearefully aſſailing it; hence it was that Chriſt man was not ſwallowed vp, becauſe the Godhead did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it: as one man may be planted in ſome ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo impregnably, that he may beare the aſſault of a whole army; ſo how ſtrong was this man which God had created within himſelfe? This muſt aboue all be thought of, this, as the rocke: The naturall Son of God is our Sauiour. Mat. 16. What ſhall the gates of hell do againſt him? The vſe of this is,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:15947:107"/> firſt, to conſider his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loue, that hath not abhorred the Virgins wombe, that hath made our fleſh and bloud a ſubſtantiall part of his perſon. If great men vouchſafe but to be free of ſome worſhipfull Company, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to be heads of ſome Corporation, it is held a great matter: but ſuppoſe there were a great kindred of poore Iacke ſtrawes which had rebelled againſt the King; ſhould the Prince match himſelfe with ſome poore maide of
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:15947:108"/> the tribe, that ſo he might pacifie the King toward them, here were grace, ſuch as no report of ſtorie could ſecond. The King of heauen hath, when we were all poore rebels, matched himſelfe with our fleſh and bloud, by couenant of perſonall cohabitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with it, neuer to be diſſolued.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, we muſt hence ſee what reaſon we haue to come to God with boldneſſe. God in himſelf is a light, to which is no acceſſe, a conſuming fire: but loe
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:15947:108"/> he hath made himſelfe God-man, that looking at thy owne nature thou mighteſt not be afraid of him. The ancient ſheepheards to make themſelues leſſe awfull, and more louely to their ſheepe, were wont to go couered with their skinnes: So this ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of our ſoules, that he might not be terrible vnto vs, maketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like vnto vs in fleſh and bloud. Though we feared ſome great man, yet were he married to our houſe, very neare vs, this circumſtance would
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:15947:109"/> animate vs not a little: thinke the ſame of thy God, married as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to thy fleſh. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as this ſheweth loue, and encourageth; ſo to conſider, that God is he that dwelleth in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will be a ground of hope againſt all euils whatſoeuer. Naked man could not helpe vs: thou muſt neuer ſtay in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man. But as when thou ſeeſt a body, thou knoweſt it is ſuch a ones body; ſo when thou imagineſt that glorious body and ſpirit, ſtill thinke whoſe they are,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:15947:109"/> the eternall Sonnes of God. On this perſon as God fixe all thy truſt; as man, thou haſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, but as God, thou haſt matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, as who cannot be withſtood in his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pleaſure toward thee: our affiance is built vpon the perſon that is man, but as he is God, not as he is man. For curſed is he that truſteth in fleſh. Laſtly, ſeeing Chriſt hath for our ſake taken our baſe nature, how equall is it, that we at his requeſt ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be partakers of
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:15947:110"/> the diuine nature, that is, of heauenly qualities and condition? Should the Prince hauing done ſuch a thing for the poore ſnakes aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, intreate nothing at them but that they would liue at Court with him, and partake in his glorie, were it not an eaſie ſuite?</p>
                     <p>The next thing that followeth, is that at Chriſt hath done and ſuffered all things for vs; euen the curſed death. We of our ſelues are bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, who ſtand indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto all obedience
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:15947:110"/> to euery commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſneſſe the Law requireth; who likewiſe are in debt to the iuſtice of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue ſinned, in debt, I ſay, ſo farre as to beare the curſed death. Curſed is he that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not in all to do it alwaies. Now God hath put himſelfe ſurety for vs, he hath in our roome bene obedient to euery commandement, if this be to be asked of vs; and he hath put his body &amp; ſoule twixt this curſed death and vs, that ſo we
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:15947:111"/> might be diſcharged. If a man do this or that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for vs when abſent, ô how kindly we take it, eſpecially if he do it out of his meere good will vnſpoken to of vs? But how ſhould we take this to heart, that Chriſt hath, when we could not through our graceleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe once aske him, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled all righteouſneſſe, which we were to fulfill? We take it as loue in men, if ſpoken to, they will do ſmall matters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for vs. Againe, he that will beare a blow in our behalfe, be bound
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:15947:111"/> for vs in great ſummes of money, eſpecially he that will lie by it for our good: but how much more are we to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this grace of Chriſt, who hath bene our ſurety, payed for our deliuerance, not ſiluer or gold, but his precious bloud? Againe, this is the ſure anchor of our faith, our ſurety hath diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all that can be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at vs. Now a debt in iuſtice once payed can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not againe be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Who then ſhall lay anything to our charge? it is Chriſt that is dead,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:15947:112"/> yea riſen from the dead for the iuſtifying of vs. He hath once ſatisfied all in the behalfe of vs who beleeue; who then ſhall be able to demand ought at vs?</p>
                     <p>The next thing is, that Chriſt alone hath done and ſuffered all things for vs; not Saints, nor our ſelues are to be Sauiours, but the glorie of this belongeth to that Name alone: ſhall duſt and aſhes beſet to helpe out the great God in that he goeth about? Let the Sunne borrow light of candels when this
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:15947:112"/> may be prooued. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer mooueth God to ſaue vs as without himſelfe, whatſoeuer ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually applieth it, all is in Chriſt. Chriſts paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the medicine, Chriſts diuine power the vertue which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all in all. True it is that faith, repentance, thankfull confeſſion are required: but firſt, not as cauſes working our ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, but as meanes without which we come not to this ſaluation. I am ſicke, there is a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician which healeth ſuch as I am onely; he
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:15947:113"/> would haue his patients haue a good perſwaſion of him, be thankfull to him, be ſorrie if they rudely prouoke him. Now ſuch he with his medicines (by his art ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the ſame) reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to health. Who would ſay, that a mans going to the Phyſician, his ſorrow for offending him, his thankfulneſſe toward him, do properly cure him of his diſeaſe? euery thing neceſſary to this or that end, is not a cauſe of that to which it concurreth as needfull. We haue need of meate
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:15947:113"/> and drinke that we may ſerue God, yet meate &amp; drinke are no cauſes of godlineſſe. Secondly, theſe things needfull are begun in vs, continued, perfected by Chriſt, the author and finiſher of faith and all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in vs. Now the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do in theſe two branches derogate from Chriſt his abſolute ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of vs. Firſt, that they make man in part to do and endure that which is the medicine healing of him. Secondly, that they make him out of the power of his wil, not
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:15947:114"/> created in him when he is onely regenerate, but remaining in his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nature, to bring forth thoſe things which are neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, that ſaluation may be applied. Let vs therefore know that in Chriſt we are compleat, and hauing ſuch an one who is able perfectly to ſaue vs, let vs not looke any other way to any creature in heauen or earth. It is Chriſt that is dead, riſen, yea that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion. If the Prince ſhould vndertake a thing, who would wiſh
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:15947:114"/> he might for his further ſecuritie haue ſome poore ſubiect ioyned with him; that which is perfect is marred by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ought vnto i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. And who will ſay that Chriſts ſufferings, righteouſnes, effectuall application are any way defectiue? Let vs then with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle care to know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Chriſt, and him crucified. A fift wheele helpeth nothing, troubleth not a little; ſo it fareth with all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſufferings that are ioyned with Chriſts,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:15947:115"/> in iuſtifying and ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for vs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="principle">
                     <head>The fourth Principle.</head>
                     <p>Q. <hi>BVt how mayeſt thou be made partaker of Chriſt and his benefits?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A. <hi>A man of a contrite and humble ſpirit, by faith alone apprehending and applying Chriſt with all his merits vnto him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, is iuſtified before God, and ſanctified.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Principle layeth downe foure things, firſt what is the qualitie of the perſon to be ſaued,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:15947:115"/> in thoſe words, a man of an humble and broken ſpirit. Secondly, the grace, by which as a meane he is ſaued, or the grace apprehending that whereby we are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, viz. faith alone. Thirdly, the thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, Chriſt &amp; his benefits. Fourthly, the fruits following vpon Chriſt and his benefits apprehended, our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the firſt, obſerue that none whoſe ſpirit is not broken with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinne, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by Chriſt. I came
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:15947:116"/> not to cal the righteous, but the ſinner; not ſuch as thinke themſelus iuſt enough, but ſuch as through my working in them ſee their ſinnes, to call thoſe to repentance. Come to me ye that are weary and heauy laden. God commanded that the Paſchall Lambe ſhould not be eaten but with bitter herbes; to teach vs that without the ſalad of godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and contrition for ſinne, Chriſt ſauoureth not. For looke as man muſt be hungry yer he will care for bread, and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:15947:116"/> muſt feele himſelfe ſicke before he will care for the Phyſitian; ſo it is with vs: if our ſoules feele not themſelues empty of all goodneſſe and ſicke of ſinne, they will not care for Chriſt, the bread of life, the Phyſitian of diſtreſſed ſoules. We muſt labour therefore to be caſt downe in the ſenſe of our miſery. Were we guilty of faults for which the law of man would ſeuerely puniſh vs, how would it go neare vs? for our breach of Gods lawes we take no care: if
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:15947:117"/> we haue loſt little things on the earth, we grieue; but to be caſt out of heauen our eternall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, this ſtingeth vs not. Such is the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſin, it is a death of the ſoule, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away ſenſe of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as in the body, the nigher death y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſer we feele, &amp; the more dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſickneſſe the leſſe it is perceiued. Againe, it doth like drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe take away the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall vnderſtanding of our miſeries. A drunken man feeleth no knocks; ſo we, the diuell hauing
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:15947:117"/> made vs drunken, feele not how we are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, obſerue what we muſt do to be ſaued, Beleeue on Chriſt. Such as would be cured of their ſtings which by ſerpents they had receiued, muſt looke vp to the ſerpent of braſſe, which God did ſet vp: So we that will be cured of the poiſon which the old ſerpent hath conueyed into vs, muſt looke to Chriſt with our eye of faith. What ſhall we do that we may be ſaued? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:15947:118"/> ſaith S. <hi>Paul.</hi> For as it is not enough that there is a Phyſitian which hath a medicine readie for this or that griefe; but the patient muſt go to him and take it: and as it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for vs being hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, to ſee and know that there is bread, but we muſt eate it if we will haue fruit by the one or other: ſo in Chriſt, we muſt come to him by faith, feede vpon him in our hearts by vnfained beleefe, before he will profit vs any thing. Wherefore let vs not
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:15947:118"/> content our ſelues with the Papiſts faith, which confeſſeth that there is a Chriſt the Sonne of God, but doth not lay hold on him as their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. This is an hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith which letteth Chriſt hang in the aire, doth not bring him to dwell in the heart. We muſt ſay with <hi>Thomas,</hi> My Lord, and my God: With <hi>Paul,</hi> Galat. 2.20. Who hath loued me, &amp; giuen himſelfe for me. For plaiſters muſt be ſpread on the ſore, and medicines taken, before the patient can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:15947:119"/> Thirdly, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that faith onely is it which as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment applying Chriſt doth ſaue vs. Not that faith goeth alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other vertues, and care of good life; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no other grace doth lay hold of Chriſt, as in whom we come to haue forgiueneſſe of ſin, &amp; life euerlaſting. (Loue indeed claſpeth Chriſt, yet not ſeeking righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and life by him, but cleauing to him for that which we diſcerne him to be vnto vs through faith:) euen as
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:15947:119"/> the eye in the head is not alone without other ſenſes, yet it onely ſeeth, and no other ſenſe with it. Which doth let vs ſee what a precious thing this faith is, as <hi>Peter</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it, and why the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell doth ſo much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour againſt it, becauſe this is it alone which ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs vnto Chriſt our Sauiour, which holdeth him as all in all to vs. Suppoſe one did hang ouer the ſea, claſping a rocke with his hands; he that wiſhed his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, need no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to looſe the hold he had
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:15947:120"/> with his hands; ſo it is with vs. Fourthly, marke what it is that faith lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hold on to ſaluation, onely Chriſt dying for vs, &amp; fulfilling all things in our behalfe. This is the onely obiect, or matter about which faith is occupied, as it is the inſtrument of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and ſauing of vs; and in regard of this that it apprehendeth, it is ſaid onely to ſaue vs. Faith iuſtifying doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the ſtory of the Bible, the threatnings of God; yea may vpon ſome particular word by
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:15947:120"/> inſtinct or otherwiſe coming to vs, worke a miracle: but it doth not iuſtifie, and ſaue vs, but onely as it looketh to Chriſt, who is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our God; not as beleeuing other things. As a reaſonable ſoule in man doth bring forth ſenſe and motion, doth concoct, expell, doth exerciſe, animall, ſenſitiue, and naturall functions in the body; yet it is not reaſonable as it doth theſe things, but as it conceiueth of things ſimple, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:15947:121"/> diſcourſeth: and in this reſpect onely it is ſaid to ſaue vs, becauſe that it layeth hold on Chriſt our Sauiour; ſo that the meaning of this, faith ſaueth vs, is, Chriſt apprehended by faith doth ſaue vs. Whence Rom. 3.9. and Act. 3.9. theſe phraſes are made aequiualent, to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Chriſt, and by faith, to be healed by the Name of Chriſt, and faith in his Name. As if one ſhould ſay, this pot of money maketh me a rich man; we would not thinke the pot made
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:15947:121"/> him rich, but the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it. So when faith is ſaid to ſaue, it is not to be meant that the act of beleeuing abſolutly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered doth ſaue vs, but reſpectiuely in regard of Chriſt our Sauiour, whom faith holdeth. Wherefore let vs onely hold Chriſt as beſide whom we lacke nothing fully to ſaue vs. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the diuell as he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth againſt faith, ſo he ſeeketh to corrupt men in reſting onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt. Hence he teacheth them to truſt on their good prayers,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:15947:122"/> ſeruing of God, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning workes; and in the popiſh Church many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, the Church treaſury, the interceſſion of Saints, humane ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, indulgences, workes; that thus he might bring them, while they catch at a ſhadow of righteouſnes, to let fal the true righteouſneſſe; as <hi>Aeſops</hi> dog making to the ſhadow of meate he ſaw in the water, let fall that which he had in his mouth. Chriſt and theſe will not ſtand together; ſo much as we lay hold on theſe, ſo much we let
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:15947:122"/> go out hold on Chriſt. Laſtly, note what bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit we haue being in Chriſt; we haue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. We by <hi>Adam,</hi> firſt ſtand guiltie of ſinne: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of euerlaſting death. Now Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene made a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſinne, that is, for the taking away of ſin, and pacifying of God his Father, doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obtaine forgiueneſſe of ſinne for vs that are his, but the grace of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and free dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life euerlaſting. Hence it is, that as by
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:15947:123"/> generation and coming of <hi>Adam</hi> we partake in ſinne and death; ſo by regeneration, being ſet into Chriſt, we are made partakers of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and life from him. And look as a griffe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh in the ſap which the ſtocke containeth, or as a member coupled vnto the head, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth in the ſenſe and motion which is thence deriued: ſo we by faith ſet into Chriſt, haue his righteouſneſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyed vnto vs, God imputing it to vs as ours; and life likewiſe conueyed from
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:15947:123"/> him the fountaine of it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ob.</hi> But then we are ſaued and made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with anothers righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as if any can be made wiſe with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wiſedome. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſts is not anothers, but after a ſort ours, when we by faith are made one with him. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, how was <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne made our ſinne? Thirdly, if the Pope be pleaſed, he may in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences impute the ſufferings &amp; righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of other men, to ſuch as neuer knew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:15947:124"/> ſhall it then be vnlawfull for God to impute to vs the righteouſneſſe of his Sonne? And it is to be noted that he ſaith: we are iuſtified, that is, haue in Chriſt forgiueneſſe of ſinne; and are ſanctified, that is, haue the life of glorie begun in vs. For grace is the beginning of eternall life, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe ſayings: To ſuch as are in Chriſt there is no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: &amp;, Who ſo belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth hath euerlaſting life: whom he hath iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thoſe alſo he hath glorified; by faith their
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:15947:124"/> hearts were purified. For looke as not onely <hi>Adams</hi> fact in eating the forbidden fruite was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to vs, but his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption which was in his nature, being the death of the ſoule, was alſo propagated to his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: ſo not only Chriſts obedience to the curſed death, is reckoned as if we had borne it, but the glorious life which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in him as a roote of it, is conueyed to vs. We ſee then what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull benefits we haue being in Chriſt. If we had faulted againſt ſome
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:15947:125"/> great man, we would count it no ſmall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to haue it releaſed &amp; freely forgiuen vs. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to be recouered vnto bodily life out of ſome great dangerous ſickneſſe, is no ſmal mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; what bleſſedneſſe then is this, to be ſet free from all our offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and of dead men in ſoule, to be made aliue to God?</p>
                     <p>Secondly, if any thirſt after theſe things, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt they go? euen to this fountaine. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marke, that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin neuer goeth
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:15947:125"/> to a man, but that clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his nature and ſanctifying of him go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it alſo. A coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoyſon coming to the heart, poyſon is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled. So Chriſt and Belial will not dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one perſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="principle">
                     <head>The fift Principle.</head>
                     <p>Q. <hi>VVHat are the ordinarie or vſuall meanes for obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of faith?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Anſw. <hi>Faith cometh onely by the preaching of the word, and increaſeth daily by it: as alſo by the
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:15947:126"/> adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and prayer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This anſwer layeth downe two things, firſt, the meane or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of begetting, and increaſing faith, viz. the word preached. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the meanes which ſerue only to the further increaſing, not to the firſt begetting of it, viz. the Sacraments and prayer. For the firſt, we may note hence that true faith is bred in vs by the hearing of the word, and nouriſhed by the ſame. Rom. 10. How can we beleeue without
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:15947:126"/> hearing? ſo the Goſpell is the powerfull inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from faith to faith, I commend you to the word which is able to build you vp. For faith is the credit and aſſent which we giue to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: now how can we giue credit to any thing we neuer heard of? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heare what is done in France till ſome meſſenger do bring vs word of it; ſo wee cannot heare what Gods pleaſure in heauen is toward vs, till he diſpatcheth his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:15947:127"/> vnto vs. The ſame word doth after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe faith in vs: for if we beleeue an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much the more, becauſe he often goeth ouer, which affirmeth this or that to vs; how much more muſt we be ſtrengthened to heare God reiterating his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of this or that which he formerly had ſpoken? Euen as in the naturall birth, the ſame bloud of the mother whereof as a ſeede it is framed, the ſame I ſay, is after her deliuery by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the kernels in
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:15947:127"/> the breaſt turned into milke, wherewith the babe is nouriſhed: ſo this word is both the ſeed which breedeth, &amp; the ſincere milke of the Goſpell which feedeth faith in vs. Yet we muſt not thinke that this word we preach is the principall worker of faith, for it is but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal inſtrument which God vſeth; which as it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not worke faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, ſo God will not worke faith without it; It hath pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue his:
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:15947:128"/> otherwiſe. Eph. 1. The ſame power which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp Ieſus from the dead, is it which brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs to beleeue. If one were borne without an hand, none could ſet a naturall hand on ſuch a body, but the power which createth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a body; ſo much leſſe can any power but the Lords, create this grace in the ſoule which is as an hand that reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into heauen. The vſe of this, is, firſt to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our faith in this point, by what meanes we found it wrought in
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:15947:128"/> our hearts, by what meane it is preſerued &amp; increaſed in vs. If it be a true faith, the word preached did beget it, &amp; it feeleth it ſelfe to grow in ſtrength by meane of the ſame word. When as many that ſay they beleeue, they neuer found any vſe of the word to begin their faith; for they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they ſay, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince yeares of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they were without a good beleefe to God-ward; neither do they feele any need of the word to grow by; the
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:15947:129"/> leſſe they haue of it, it is the better with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſuch mens faith is a diuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh deluſion. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we haue come to our faith by hearing, &amp; find that the word is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall in vs to the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of it in vs; in all this, it is with vs as it is with true beleeuers. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we ſee how needfull the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched is for vs; no word, no faith; no faith, no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. This maketh the diuell ſo malicious to perſwade the contempt of it, or at leaſt to beare vs in hand that it is not
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:15947:129"/> ſo neceſſary. What, were none ſaued that had not Preachers? may we not reade, &amp; pray at home, and ſerue God without this? who are worſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many that gad after it? What can they tell thee more then thou knoweſt? They ſpeake great things of it, but what doſt thou feele? He knoweth that if he can keepe vs from attending on the Word, we ſhall neuer be brought to faith, and ſo neuer haue benefit by Chriſt Ieſus. Wherefore let vs come within this net; and if
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:15947:130"/> we be already borne to God, let vs like new borne babes crie after this milke that we may grow by it. Secondly, note that by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments our faith is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in vs. For euen as men do further ſecure thoſe they deale with, by putting to their ſeale vnto their couenants; ſo God, willing to giue vs full aſſurance, hath not contented himſelfe to make a will paneld by word onely, but hath written it, yea hath by oath confirmed it by the witneſſe of his Spirit. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:15947:130"/> hath put to his ſeale, that nothing might be wanting which might the better ſecure vs; and all this is not to make his word more ſure in it ſelfe, but to make it more ſure in our perſwaſion. This is the vſe of Sacraments; for the Scripture calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Couenant, ſignes of the Couenant, ſignes &amp; ſeales of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſignes confirming the weakeneſſe of our beleefe, ratifying Gods couenants with vs; not diſtinguiſhing onely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="252" facs="tcp:15947:131"/> vnbeleeuers (which is Anabaptiſtrie) nor yet inſtruments infuſing the firſt grace into vs; for <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of all the faithfull, now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a beleeuer, receiued circumciſion: ſo <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> now an approoued beleeuer, was baptized; and we neuer find the fruite of our Baptiſme or the Lords ſupper, till we be taught to beleeue. This then ſhould teach vs both to acknowledge Gods great grace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, that thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendeth to our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. If a man of worth
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:15947:131"/> be not beleeued on his word, eſpecially if he giue a deed of his hand, he will ſnuffe at it, not take it well; but our God who cannot lie, dealeth otherwiſe. As alſo we muſt reioyce to come vnto theſe Sacraments: ſhould we come to haue the ſeale paſſed of ſome great earthly matter made ouer to vs, how would we reioyce? ſhall we not be glad when we come to haue the ſeales which aſſure to vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all our ſinnes, and life euerlaſting? Thirdly, we muſt hence giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:15947:132"/> to God, in beleeuing him without all doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and vncertaintie, which popiſh religion perſwadeth. If an honeſt man ſhould giue vs his word, deed, oath, before witneſſe ſhould ſeale this or that; would we not be aſhamed to be incredulous? Much more ſhamefull it is to diſtruſt the liuing God.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly marke, faith is increaſed by prayer, not begotten, for we cannot pray to him on whom we haue not beleeued; it is the firſt fruit that faith bringeth. When
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:15947:132"/> babes are borne, they ſay they crie preſently; but when by faith once the babe of the new creature is borne in vs, it preſently crieth, Lord helpe my vnbeleefe; I beleeue Lord, Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe my faith. And as children haue no more compendious way to get any thing then to beg it at their parents, no more haue we then to beg at our God; who, if parents ſinfull giue good things to their children that aske them, will much more giue vs his Spirit that deſire it.
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:15947:133"/> Let vs then beg increaſe of this and all other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Spare to ſpeake, and ſpare to ſpeed; open thy mouth wide, and God will fill it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="principle">
                     <head>The ſixt Principle.</head>
                     <p>Q. <hi>VVHat is the eſtate of all men after death?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A. <hi>All men ſhall ariſe againe with their owne bodies, to the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which being ended, the godly ſhall poſſeſſe the kingdome of heauen: but vnbeleeuers and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates ſhall be in hell, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:15947:133"/> with the diuell &amp; his Angels for euer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hauing thus inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely laid downe our ſtate by nature, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly handled our eſtate preſent by grace, he now vnfoldeth what ſhall be the future eſtate of man in glorie, or end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe torment. In the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer three things are laid downe as matters to be beleeued; firſt, the generall reſurrection of vs all; ſecondly, the end to which we are raiſed, that we may come to iudgement: thirdly, the things which ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:15947:134"/> vpon iudgement: viz. the execution of Chriſts ſentence, both touching the bleſſednes of the faithfull, and the curſed damnation of the wicked. For the firſt marke this, what we are to perſwade our ſelues of our bodies and the bodies of all other, viz. that they ſhall at length be raiſed vp. This reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, and of euery mans own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per body to himſelfe, is a point of beleefe grounded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and power of God, which can ſubdue all
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:15947:134"/> things to it ſelfe. Yet ſounder reaſon may make it probable: for as the ſeede ſowne doth not ſo corrupt that it ſhould come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that a new body may be ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; ſo our bodies do not returne to duſt, that ſo they might vaniſh to nothing, but that ſo in their time they might through Gods power fpring vp into immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and ſtrong bodies. And why is it not as cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible to think that God can bring againe all thoſe bodies that haue
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:15947:135"/> bene, as to be perſwaded that he can create new generations of bodies that neuer yet had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? for, that this ſhould be, which ſometime hath bene, is not more maruellous then that ſuch a thing ſhould be, which neuer yet had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the nature of things. He that ſhould ſee a little portion of ſeede in a glaſſe, and ſhould ſee the portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a perfect man, (ſay he had neuer ſeene the procreation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) he would as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue that euer ſuch
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:15947:135"/> ſeede ſhould become ſuch a creature, as that duſt ſhould be raiſed vp, had he no more ſeene the one then the other. But God hath ſpoken it, and his power can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all things to it ſelfe; and theſe two are the props of our beleefe in this point. Now though all ſhall be raiſed vp, yet in diuers manner, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ends; theſe by Chriſt as a head bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaluation, thoſe by him as a iudge of all fleſh: theſe to glory, thoſe other to ſhame. For as for the wicked it
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:15947:136"/> were better for them if they did not riſe; as Chriſt ſaith, it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>Iudas</hi> he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene.</p>
                     <p>The vſe of this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to the godly, they die not to be held for euer vnder it, but to riſe more glorious. Who doth not endure to haue an old houſe pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe, that may haue a new built vp in the roome? Who taketh it grieuouſly to lie downe to ſleepe, that knoweth he ſhall riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the morning? Yea this is true, if wee
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:15947:136"/> could be as ſure of this our riſing, as we are of the other. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why ſhould we doubt? God hath ſaid it, who gaue being to all things out of nothing, and can much more make vs this or that, being ſomthing. Againe, reaſon doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it as being not abſurd. Finally, thou haſt in thy ſelfe alreadie the firſt reſurrection of thy ſoule from death in ſinne, which is greater; wilt thou not then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that he whom thou haſt found able to raiſe thy ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:15947:137"/> in ſinne, is able to raiſe vp thy body likewiſe? And it is terrible to the wicked; it were well with them if death coming there were an end. Nay the body muſt riſe, that as it was partaker with the ſoule in ſinning, ſo it may be partaker with it in iudgement.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond thing is the end to which all are raiſed, to iudgment. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue then, that euery one ſhall come before Ieſus Chriſt the great God to iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes haue their Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticers riding their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits,
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:15947:137"/> and in fit times iudging all cauſes, and perſons ſubiect to iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So God hath his Chriſt, to whom he hath committed all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who ſhall come gloriouſly from heauen in his time, and iudge all fleſh righteouſly. And needs it muſt be, for here in this life is not ſeene, the puniſhment of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, nor the reward of vertue. Now if a King in his common wealth cannot iuſtly ſuffer ſin vnpuniſhed, nor vertue without encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, how much leſſe ſhall the
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:15947:138"/> iuſt God let the wicked carry it away for euer, &amp; the godly vnrewarded? ſhall not the iuſt Iudge of all the world ſet all at right in his time? But the Scripture ſaith, that he that beleeueth ſhall not come into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Ioh. 5. and that he who beleeueth not, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready condemned. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The righteous ſhall not come into iudgment of condemnation, but he ſhall appeare to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally and publikely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued. The wicked is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready iudged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the word, in
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:15947:138"/> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, <hi>Sententia Iudicis interloquutoria,</hi> not <hi>definitiua.</hi> The word iudgeth him, his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence condemneth him, but the definitiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is not ſolemnly pronounced. This then is to be thought on, that God will haue all brought to iudgement, yea he ſhall reckon with malefactors to the leaſt idle word. As malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are brought out of darkſome priſons, ſo ſhall the bodies &amp; ſoules of wicked ones be drawne forth of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of hell &amp; the graue,
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:15947:139"/> to receiue their doome. This not thought vpon, men are bold to commit wickedneſſe, as we ſay, the theefe wots not the hemp groweth when he ſtealeth. Many thinke, let them haue but this day, they will make ſhift good enough; but the more thou preſumeſt, the more ſhalt thou be confounded; the lighter thou ſetteſt by it, thou ſhalt feele it the more vnſupportable. We are afraid to fall into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lapſe, to do any thing amiſſe which we are ſure to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before our betters,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:15947:139"/> if we do it: how is it then that we are not afraid, to do any thing, though we muſt anſwer it before God? This is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable to the godly, that they haue yet an appeale ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a higher iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then vpon the earth.</p>
                     <p>The laſt thing follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the glory of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, the eternal dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. When ſentence is once paſſed in earthly affaires, forthwith there are inferiour officers, which ſee execution ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: ſo when this great God hath paſſed
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:15947:140"/> his ſentence, he hath good and euill Angels which ſhall be executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto him. Firſt, the godly ſhall enter their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall liſe, and be made partakers with Chriſt in his glory: for, this is part of their dignity, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould as benchers ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with Chriſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaude his moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement on wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones, who haue not beleeued, nor obeyed the Goſpell; and ſo after a ſort iudge the world with Chriſt. Know ye not that the Saints ſhall iudge the world? Now
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:15947:140"/> their eternall life is a thing we beleeue. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue life euerlaſting; for if a man do out of his bounty giue often to ſome ſeruitor that hath done him the better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, a free hold to him and his heires after him for euer, and ſo (if the world could be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to continue, and his name not to grow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct,) an euerlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; how much more doth it agree with Gods bountie to recompence the momentany ſeruices of his children, with gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this euerlaſting
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:15947:141"/> inheritance, which out of his fatherly loue he before worlds prepared for them? Here then is matter of ioy, the beſt diſh is to come, our life is yet hid; we liue now as a tree in winter, whoſe life is hid at the roote of it, ſo is ours with God in Chriſt, the roote of vs: but when the Spring of our reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh, it ſhall be manifeſted.</p>
                     <p>Finally, marke what is the end of wicked ones, eternall damnation with the diuell and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. I ſhewed in the end of the ſecond queſtion,
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:15947:141"/> how it is meete that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentany wicked ones ſhould haue euerlaſting puniſhment; for it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an infinite and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall maieſtie: &amp; kings may iuſtly puniſh with perpetuall impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which a man ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer endure, could he be ſuppoſed to liue alwaies. What paine ſhall here be, when the paine of one tooth may be ſo great as ſeemeth vnſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable; what ſhall it be when euery part ſhal be filled with ſuch horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble griefe as neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:15947:142"/> man? To ſee one diuell often, is ſo fearefull that it exanimateth thoſe that behold it; what ſhal be this horror, when the ſoule and body ſhall liue in one manſion with the diuell and all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and be tormented by them for euer? for euer, euer while God is God, no hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. To be put by little things and miſſe our marke in this or that earthly hope, how doth it grieue vs? but to be put by the ioyes of heauen, the bleſſed fellowſhip of God, his Angels, the
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:15947:142"/> righteous, how ſhall this ſting vs? When after-thought, of hauing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhot our ſelues in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle matters, doth go ſo neare vs, that we are in a hell for the time; what ſhall it be when this thought ſhall vexe vs, to thinke of our follies in reiecting, and not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding eternall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe when it was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs? The Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore keepe vs from ſin; it is ſweet, but the ſawce is ſowre, this laſt diſh will marre the feaſt: a wofull ſhot will come in for vs, who learne not
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:15947:143" rendition="simple:additions"/> to know God, our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtates, and with ſorrowfull hearts to flie to his mercies in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15947:143"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
